<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caveat for the couetous. Or, A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, vpon the fourth of December, out of Luke. 12. 15. By William Whatelie, preacher of the word of God, in Banbury</title>
            <title>Caveat for the covetous.</title>
            <author>Whately, William, 1583-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25300.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841435</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841435</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14996)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 602:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caveat for the couetous. Or, A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, vpon the fourth of December, out of Luke. 12. 15. By William Whatelie, preacher of the word of God, in Banbury</title>
                  <title>Caveat for the covetous.</title>
                  <author>Whately, William, 1583-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 133, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Thomas Man, and Mathew Lawe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition there is an additional preface.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 25300a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6017:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6017:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT FOR THE COVETOVS. <hi>OR,</hi> A SERMON PREACHED at <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe, vpon the fourth of <hi>December,</hi> out of <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.15.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM WHATELIE, Preacher of the word of God, in <hi>Banbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>The loue of the world is enmitie againſt God.</l>
               <l>You cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Man,</hi> and <hi>Mathew Lawe,</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6017:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6017:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE COVRTEOVS Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian READER,</hi> Nothing is more lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the worldlineſſe of vs Chriſtians. Our life is little elſe but a breach of our moſt ſolemne vow to the Lord of life. Wee renounced the world at our firſt entrance into the Church of God, deuoting our ſelues to the ſeruice of Chriſt. (Theſe were good words, if there were any thing beſides words in the moſt of vs.) But being growne wee renounce Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the ſeruice of the world in all our actions. Our deeds proue that wee doe but onely talke of God and Chriſt, and heauen: for what hath God but our breath? and with what doe wee ſeeke heauen, but with the tongue? the world hath heart and hands, and (if not all yet) moſt of all our ſtrength. Being therefore (againſt my will, and earneſt
<pb facs="tcp:6017:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>entreatie to the contrary) commaunded to ſpeak vnto this great congregation, I thought I could not diſcharge mine owne dutie, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the preſent auditorie better, than if I did labour to beate downe this vice, which hath gotten more ground againſt the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, (I thinke) then the diuels whole hoaſt of luſts beſides. If I haue offended in any thing, it is in being too plaine: which whether it be a fault, yea or no, in a preacher, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not determine with my ſelfe, but I know well it is leſſe faulty, then that other extreame which in our times is more in price and vſe. Yet me thinkes the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath giuen vs a very good direction, ſaying; <hi>it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue the beleeuers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> Doth the Apoſtle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace Gods ordinance by giuing it ſuch a name? or doth hee not rather deride mens cenſures that ſo miſcall it? For not the wiſe, not the learned, not the wittie, not the elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent kinde of preaching, doth helpe mens ſoules to heauen; but that kinde, which the greateſt part (out of their fleſhlineſſe) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme baſe and fooliſh, becauſe it wants the excellencie of words, &amp; the enticing ſpeeches of mans wiſedome, as elſewhere the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith; <hi>If I ſhould aime at any other
<pb facs="tcp:6017:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>end in preaching, then the ſaluation of men: were I not accurſed for doing Gods work negligently, or peruerſely?</hi> If ayming at this, I ſhould vſe any but his owne meanes, were I not fooliſh, that would prefer mine own thoughts to his? If this kind of preaching pleaſe God, why not ſpeaker? why not hearer? why not all? If it ſaue men, why ſhould it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thoſe that come, the one to offer, the other to ſeeke ſaluation? To ſay the truth, I doe not vnwillingly confeſſe, that my learning is but ſmall: For much learning requireth much reading, &amp; much reading many yeares, which all that know me, know to be wanting vnto me. Wherefore to make ſhew of much (by the helpe of an index or ſuch like) when I haue it not, were but a couſoning tricke, and a pranke beſeeming a bragger or a bankerout, of whom <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe rich and hath nothing.</hi> But ſay I had had the greateſt abundance of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet it behoued me to remember, that a pulpit is not a place to ſhew ſchollerſhip in, but faithfulnes, nor to declare how well read we are in other authours, but how ill practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the hearers are in the will and word of God the beſt author. Preaching was not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to tickle the eare with a gay ſpeech
<pb facs="tcp:6017:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>and learned oration, but to peirce the heart, with a ſharpe reproofe and earneſt exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to winne credit and applauſe to the ſpeaker; but to work knowledge and obedience in the hearer: not to make the auditorie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vs, and ſay, <hi>ſure hee is a good Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, a man of good wit and great reading, &amp;c.</hi> But to condemne themſelues, and ſay wee haue beene bad men, men of polluted hearts and liues. In a word, not to draw men to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the gifts of him that ſpeaketh, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him preferment; but to repent of their owne ſinnes, and offer ſubmiſſion vnto Chriſt that ſent him to ſpeake. This if the Miniſter aime at, hee is happy, and the people alſo, if he attaine it; but whoſoeuer aimes at credit or profit in preaching, may goe from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit to hell, and take his wages with the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite to whom it is ſaide, that he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his reward. Loth would I be to buy praiſe or profit at ſuch a price, neyther did I dare to hazard my ſelfe vnto God, for miſintending his ordinance, and handling his word in a wrong manner. With this determination did I come to ſpeake; with this determination ſhould euery Chriſtian come to heare. And if any twit me with the name of an Engliſh Preacher (a name taken vp to diſgrace the
<pb facs="tcp:6017:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>fooliſhnes of preaching which God commends) I haue to anſwere, that I ſpeake to Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and, the moſt, no Schollers, otherwiſe it had not beene hard to haue heaped vp, and learned by heart, and ſpoken readily many a Greeke and Latin ſentence fit for the purpoſe: but who would looſe labor and time, &amp; make two ſpeakings where one would ſerue the turne? And in this plaine manner <hi>(Reader)</hi> haue I encountred, by the ſword of the ſpirit, this capital euill of the world, which is world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe I was willing to publiſh, being ſpoken, what I was not willing to ſpeake, hoping to helpe ſome man againſt the ſinne, (which I ſpeake againſt) beſides mine hearers, if but one Chriſtian grow leſſe earthly by benefit of this labour, my recompence is ſufficient; if not one, yet I haue this fruite that I intended to doe good and endeauoured it. Now <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou meete with any fault, cenſure it with fauour, for I am but a man, and in reading apply nothing to any, but to thy ſelfe, &amp; I haue my deſire. Thus I commend thee, and thy grouth in vertue, to the helpe and aſſiſtance of our gracious Father. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Banbury, <date>Ianuary.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian affection,</hi> William Whately.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6017:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6017:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>M. VVHATELIES SERMON, PREACHED AT PAVLES CROSSE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 12.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Take heede and beware of couetouſneſſe, for though a man haue aboundance, his life conſiſts not in his riches.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered vpon occaſion of a certaine accident related immediatly before. Two brethren were at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, about their fathers lands. It ſeemes that one would haue had all to himſelfe, and left very little or nothing to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hereupon the party that thought himſelfe wronged, entreats our Sauiour by good counſell, to compoſe the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betwixt them, and to bring his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6017:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſome more equall courſe of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Our Lord that alwaies regarded the the ſoule more than the ſtate, perceiuing couetouſneſſe to be the cauſe of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, refuſeth to intermeddle with the parting of their lands, and fals to cure that diſeaſe of their ſoules which procured all this diſtemper. This he begins to doe in the verſe preſent, and proſecutes more at large in the ſequel of the Chapter. Theſe words diuide themſelues into two parts: The firſt, Chriſts exhortation, <hi>Take heed, and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi> The ſecond, the reaſon wherewith he backs his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation taken from the ineffectualneſſe of wealth, the obiect of couetouſneſſe, <hi>for though a man haue aboundance, &amp;c.</hi> that is, if any man ſhould heape vp all ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, hee ſhall finde no more ſafety, quiet, or contentment of life, from this his cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heaped plenty of outward things. The point of doctrine which our Sauiour Chriſt aimes at, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> in the diſcuſsing of which I purpoſe to ſpend the time alotted, is ſo manifeſt, that no man can chuſe but ſee it, whoſoeuer will be ruled by Chriſt, muſt beware of Couetouſneſſe. All true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that doe hang at Chriſts mouth for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6017:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>direction, and ſhew their hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by practiſe of obedience, muſt ſhun and auoide with al diligence this hatefull ſinne of worldlineſſe; one word of Chriſt ſhould be ſufficient to a Chriſtian ſoule, but he was not ſo ſcant of words as once onely to warne vs of ſuch a capitall euill. The ſame ſpirit ſpake in his Apoſtles, that in himſelfe and by their mouthes he hath giuen vs many like aduertiſements, whereof ſome one or two it ſhall ſuffice to haue mentioned. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.5. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks to Chriſtians in this manner. <hi>Mortifie therefore your earthly members, fornication, vncleanneſſe, inordinate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, euill concupiſcence, and couetouſneſſe,</hi> which, (to prouoke our greater hatred) he cals by that hatefull name of idolatry. And well might he ſo call it, for it cauſeth a man to repoſe his hope of ſafetie vpon riches, which ſhould be wholy and onely fixed vpon the Lord of hoaſts, ſeeing it is impoſsible that any thing ſhould ſecure a man from danger, vnleſſe it doe ſurpaſſe all other thinges in power and in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: this ſinne is you ſee a capitall eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of our ſaluation, which in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian warfare we ſhould fight againſt, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6017:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtriue to ſlaughter in our ſelues. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle alſo, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. hath ſaide to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Let your conuerſation be without couetouſnes.</hi> The word is in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall, <hi>without the loue of mony.</hi> But all comes to one reckoning. And it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable that he ſaith (your conuerſation,) to meete with the deceitfull hollowneſſe of thoſe that content themſelues in ſome few actions to appeare not couetous, whilſt in other actions at other times they be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly polluted with this ſin. Their counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit and maymed diligence, anſweres not the large extent of this commandement. A good mans life if Gods counſell might be heard, ſhould not in one or two alone, but in all the parts thereof, bee free from the ſtaines of this wickedneſſe. More pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might be produced for the proofe of the ſame truth, if it were as needfull, as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſo to doe. But the chiefe difficultie in this thing will bee, not ſo much to winne conſent of iudgement to the point, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of practiſe to the iudgement. Wherfore to the intent that Chriſts ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may bee more profitably regarded, and this fault more carefully ſhunned by you all that heare me this day; I will in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6017:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>few words ſet out ſome of the moſt harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful effects that enſue vpon this vicious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of minde that Chriſt cals coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> it vtterly hinders the ſauing ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the word of God, and cauſeth the moſt powerfull inſtrument of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſaluation, to be altogether inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall for the producing of theſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, in that party in whom it beareth ſway. That our Sauiour plainely witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, when he compareth the word to ſeed, the Preacher to the ſeedſman, the heart to the ground, this couetouſnes to the thornes that choake the ſeede. The Husbandman may caſt away graine vpon a parcell of land ouer-runne with brambles, but the ſeede ſo beſtowed will neuer come in at harueſt: So the Miniſter may preach the word to worldly minded men; but he ſhall ſpend his ſtrength in vaine. Let vs ſtudy neuer ſo painefully, teach neuer ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, proue neuer ſo ſtrongly, exhort neuer ſo powerfully, this time and labour is but loſt, among our earthly affected hearers. Eyther they come not to heare, or attend not in hearing, or meditate not after hearing. And this you muſt marke
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6017:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>brethren, that euen attentiue hearing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meditation will not ingraffe the word into your hearts, it will not profit the ſoule more, than much getting when a man keeps nothing can benefit his eſtate. Well may it increaſe ſwimming, but not ſauing knowledge: it may furniſh ones head with wordes and matter for honeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but not ones heart with vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſinceritie for godly conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus then ſtands the caſe. The Lord offers thee his word to enlighten thy mind, to ſanctifie thine heart, to conuert thy ſoule, and make thee a true Chriſtian: Couetouſnes oppoſeth it ſelfe, &amp; will not ſuffer the word to dwell in thine heart, nor thine heart to ponder vpon the word, and ſo cauſeth thee to be but an hypocrite at the beſt, ſhouldeſt thou not auoide it?</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> another euill as bad as this comes vp together with this. This ſinne ſteales away the heart from heauen, and thoſe deſirable graces of Gods ſpirit that fit a man for heauen.<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.2.</note> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth vs to ſet our affections vpon the things that are aboue, and not vpon the things that are below; intimating an vtter impoſsibilitie to doe both; as if hee had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6017:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>told vs that there be 2. ſorts of obiects, after which mens affections are carried, ſome are of the earth earthly, momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, tranſitorie, and vnable to giue any ſound and laſting contentment. Such are houſes, lands, goods, money, in a word, worldly things. Others are from heauen, heauenly, ſubſtantiall, conſtant, immortall, truely profitable to the whole man, ſuch are faith, repentance, the ſpirit of prayer, the fauour of God, in a word, Chriſt and his benefites. And wee muſt vnderſtand this, that the body may aſcend and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend at the ſame time, as well as the ſoule or affections goe earthward and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward both at once; Where the treaſure is, there will be the heart, bee it in heauen or in earth: no man hath two hearts, two treaſures, the one is but counterfait, if any at all. Nowe this couetouſneſſe as an arrow ſhot from hell, doth nayle the heart to the very ground, that it cannot bee lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpwards, and as a lime-twig ſet by the Diuell ſo intangles the wings of the ſoule, that it cannot poſsibly fly vpward toward its proper home. The worldly man is ſo taken vp in courting and wooing his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotry miſtreſſe, the world; which hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6017:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>taken him with her eyelids of gaine, and inueigled him with her naked breaſts of commoditie, that the ſuite for heauen and things thereof, is altogether neglected and forſaken. Therefore the ſcripture cals the worldling an adulterer, becauſe as the whoremaiſter leaues a beautifull and wel-conditioned wife, to embrace a common and polluted curtizan, ſo doth hee aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don God and ſaluation, to ſatisfie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with this moſt deformed and miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen world. And is it not the higheſt degree of vnhappineſſe to be robbed of ones vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and be ſo farre forth infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate as to exchange heauen it ſelfe for a few ſhillings, yea farthings; and be more pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and earneſt to get a little gliſtring ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into the cheſt, than the glorious image of Ieſus Chriſt into the ſoule? for though God doe often caſt theſe outward things vpon thoſe that take no great paines for them and the world fals into the mouthes of many before they bee aware of it, (as we ſay) yet it is not ſo for heauenly things. God neuer ſpilles ſuch treaſures, nor parts with them to any without ſuite, without thankes. He muſt call for wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and dig for vnderſtanding that will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6017:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue them, and ſtriue to enter that hopes to finde a place in heauen, and miſſe of his entrance that ſtriueth not. The caſe ſtands ſo therefore with thy ſoule, God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelfe and eternall life vnto thee, vpon condition of conuenient diligence in vſing the meanes to get it on thy part: the world ſteppes betwixt, drawes thine heart, diuerts thy thoughts, cares, deſires, an other way, and ſo cauſeth thee to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit euen an eternall kingdome, not for want of meanes, but of care and paines to attaine the ſame. Oughteſt thou not as Chriſt bids, to take heede thereof? but yet more euill proceedeth from this mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter euill: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> It expoſeth that heart which harbours it, with allowance vnto all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of loathſome ſinnes and dangerous temptations. The Deuill hath the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man alwayes vpon the hip, as wee ſpeake; that is, euer at ſuch an aduantage, that he doubts not to giue him the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw in any aſſault. Satan is a cruell fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, hauing his nets and his call, and euery thing in readineſſe, and if once he become acquainted with the birds diet, he makes no queſtion of his game: yea, he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe to haue the poore fowles
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6017:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>necke betweene his fingers ſpeedily. And indeed no hawke is better trayned to the fiſt of the cuning fawkner, than the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man to all the Diuels wayes; whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſinne he would haue him commit, let him but hollow &amp; caſt vp the lure of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, he ſtoupes preſently and fals vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. Would he haue him lie, promiſe him profit; then begins hee to hem and haw, and faulter in his ſpeech, and equiuocate, and at length proceedes to downe-right lying, and impudent facing out a knowne vntruth. Would he haue him periured, the ſame art doth that alſo; ſhew him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, vſe ſiluer perſwaſions, he will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay and goe backe, and feare, and ſweat, but at laſt hardens himſelfe, and cares not to pollute the name of God, with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand falſhoods, and a thouſand oathes. Yea, the Diuel can make ſuch a man wade vp to the chinne in a ſtreame of warme blood, with the gliſtring ſhewe of gold, and cauſe him to leape headlong into the bottomleſſe and burning pit of hell, with the large hope of enriching his eſtate. In a word, there is not the rankeſt of all Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans poyſons, but hee will greedily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure in the ſweet broth of commoditie.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6017:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thoſe vnnaturall crimes which would make the ſoule agaſt, if they came bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, ſend them in a guilded vizard, as it were in a maske to the couetous mans houſe, he will entertaine them kindely with a kiſſe, &amp; feares not to imbrace them euen in both his armes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe hideous and enormious euils for which hell it ſelfe doth gape vpon the conſcience with an open mouth, are (we ſee it with our eyes) euen feareleſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in hope of aduantage. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture cals this ſinne, not a braunch, but a roote, which it ſelfe, hath many large, and big, and fruitfull braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and that not of ſome one or two, or few, but of all euill: becauſe there can be no ſinne named ſo hatefull, which profit hath not made the louers of profit, either to commit themſelues, or, which is all one, to conſent to in others. The worldling is a fit peece of timber for any place in Sathans building. This mercenary ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour doth neuer thinke himſelfe too good for any ſeruice in all the Diuels campe, where pay and bootie may be gotten. He can make an Image-worſhipper, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of Image-worſhippe, a periured
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6017:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſon, a Sabboth-breaker, and a maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of them that doe it, a killer of Father and mother, a murderer of Kings, a blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vp of Parliament houſes, a ſtaruer of ſoules, a whoremaiſter, an harlot, a more polluted wretch, a robber, a forſworne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, and what not in the higheſt degree againſt any commaundement? This ſinne is like a great beaſt that makes a large gap for any other beaſt to enter in at after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. This is the Diuels great Ordinance wherewith hee makes ſuch fearefull batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vpon the wals of the conſcience, that there are many wide breaches for all his armie of other luſts, to giue an irreſiſtable aſſault thereat, vpon the heart and life and ſo to winne the ſame to himſelfe. So that whereas God forbids all ſinne in paine of damnation, the Diuell may perſwade thee if thou be couetous, to any ſinne, in hope of commoditie, and ſhouldſt not thou ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre this moſt pernicious vice?</p>
            <p>But neyther yet is this all. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> A man might begin to practiſe ſinnes, and yet after feeling the bitterneſſe of theſe pathes of death, returne back into the wayes of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, and be ſafe. But this ſinne is like the harlot, a deepe and narrow ditch, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6017:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>like the wicked woman that <hi>Salomon</hi> cals more bitter then death, whoſe heart is as nets and ſnares, and her hands as bands to keepe a man faſt in the ward and priſon of the diuell. For in the fourth place, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is ouer-ruled by this ſinne, cannot tread one of the ſure ſteps towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and in what meaſure this lead is tyed to any mans heeles, he is vtterly diſabled from climing vp the ladder of bleſſednes, which the Scripture hath framed for vs. You know that our Sauiour Chriſt hath ſhewed eight beatitudes, as it were ſo many ſtaires vp to the throne of heauen; to bee poore in ſpirit, to mourne ſpiritually, to be meeke, to hunger and thirſt after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to be mercifully, to be pure in heart, to be a peace-maker, and to ſuffer perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake. Now the couetous man cannot lift vp the legs of his ſoule to any one of theſe ſtaires, and therefore whileſt hee continues couetous, there is no poſsibilitie of his ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to God. Poore in ſpirit hee cannot be: For hee is ſo taken vp with feare of pouertie in purſe, and the ſenſe of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie which want will bring, that his ſoule growes altogether ſenſeleſſe of the miſery
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6017:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>into which the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> and his owne ſinnes haue caſe him. Spiritual pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury is not felt there, where want and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie are ſo extreamely pinching. Again, hee can neuer mourne truly for his ſinnes: for eyther carnall ioy) which hee takes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately by ſeeing the encreaſe of his worldly ſubſtance (as the rich man in the Goſpell, when hee thought hee had riches laid vp in ſtore for many yeeres) doth ſo tickle and warm his heart that the ſtreame of tears is dryed vp, which ſhould be ſpent in bewailing his ſinnes: or elſe that world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorrow and vexation (that ſtinges him vpon the ſenſe of outward croſſes, and the diſappointment of his hopes in earthly matters) doth turne the ſtreame of weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite another way, that it cannot come to the waſhing of his ſoule, and purging of his conſcience, Then meeke he cannot be, for he is alwaies poſſeſſed with one or other paſsion of carnall ioy, or griefe, or enuie, or the like, which as a ſtorme or tempeſt on the ſea doth fil him ful of rage and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. The ſpirit of God hath called him a trouble houſe, ſaying, hee that is greedy of gaine troubles his owne houſe, and it is impoſsible that his heart ſhould be meeke
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6017:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and quiet, when as hee cannot ſuffer his houſe ſo to be. Alſo for hungring and thirſting after righteouſneſſe, it cannot be that his appetite ſhould ſtand that way, for the doges-hunger, and dropſie-thirſt of wealth doth ſo gnaw &amp; torment his ſoule, that he hath no leiſure to long for Chriſt, and the imputation or communication of his righteouſneſſe. So that he may freely lap in the filthy puddles of the world, he neuer cares for the ſweet and wholeſome ſtreames to which Ieſus Chriſt doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite him, and if the may gorge himſelf with the foule garbage of ill gotten goods, the pleaſant and delightfull foode of the ſoule is but vnſauery to him. And like as one that hath the greene ſickneſſe, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch diſeaſe, will leaue the beſt meat, to feede on ſalt, oat-meale, or ſome ſuch like vnwholeſome thing: ſo the pallate and ſtomacke of his ſoule is in that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure diſordered, as he will reiect righteouſneſſe it ſelfe, to ſurfet vpon filthy lucre. But as for being mercifull, that ſtands not in any ſort with his profeſsion, if he ſhould ſuffer his heart to relent at the miſeries of diſtreſſed men, and open his purſe to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6017:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>releeue them, that would ſurely leſſen the heape of his money, which hee muſt not dare to doe. A peece of money goes from him as drop of bloud from his heart, with ſuch a liuely feeling and paine, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well pleaſed with that whatſoeuer, which draws it away. And therfore he hath eyther no pittie and mercie, or elſe but by ſtarts and fits now and then, which is as good as none. Now for puritie of heart, how can it bee conceiued that hee ſhould haue it, whoſe ſoule is as neſt for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, or a cage of vncleane birds, in vvhich ſinne and Sath an may ſit, and hatch, and hurke, and bring vp all their broodes of damnable luſts and practiſes, if that they will lay now and then a golden egge or two among, for the ſatisfying of his greedy humour? Hee that hath the roote of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in his heart, cannot haue a pure heart. Moreouer for peace making, croſſe him in his penny, and hee will trouble all the world, neyther can hee put vp a wrong that toucheth him in his commoditie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, being auenged. All the world can tell that couetouſneſſe is the father, mother, nurſe and all, of moſt debates and ſtrifes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6017:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>for it makes a man ſet againſt euery man, from whom he may wreſt any prſofit, and ſtand againſt euery man alſo to whom he ſhould pay any dues. And for the laſt ſtep of all, which is to ſuffer perſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake, this he will neuer do, his goods are his God, &amp; if it come to thoſe termes that eyther he muſt leaue riches or righteouſneſſe, with true religion and the practiſe of it, he loues God well, but his mony better. Alas, he muſt be borne with, God giues good words indeed, but a man cannot liue with words: his mony hee can feele &amp; ſee, that pleaſeth his ſenſe ſo well, that he thinkes it folly to part with it, for ſuch a matter. And therefore as the young man in the Goſpell, hee hangs his head in his boſome, and goes his wayes with a ſad countenance, ſomething ſory that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe Chriſt, and keepe his wealth both, but what euer come of it, hee muſt keepe that. The world is his miſtreſſe, and he muſt imbrace her, then farewell righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and religion. So that now a man might very truly turne the ſpeeches of our Sauiour Chriſt againſt the couetous man and ſay: Curſed be the couetous for he is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6017:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>not poore but proud in ſpirit, &amp; therfore the kingdome of hell is his: curſed be the couetous, for hee cannot mourne for his ſins but for his loſſes onely, and therefore he ſhal neuer be comforted. Curſed be the couetous, for he is not meeke but froward in heart, and therefore he ſhall not inherite the earth which he ſo much wiſheth. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the couetous, for hee doth not long after righteouſneſſe, but after riches, and therefore he ſhall neuer be ſatisfied. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the couetous, for he is not merciful, but hard-hearted, and therefore hee ſhall finde no mercy. Curſed be the couetous, for he is not a peace-maker but a make-bate, and therefore hee ſhall be called the childe of the Diuell. Curſed be the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, for he is not pure but filthy in heart, and therfore he ſhall neuer ſee God. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the couetous, for hee cannot ſuffer the loſſe of his wealth for righteouſneſſe ſake, and therefore the kingdome of hell is his. Muſt you not then needs yeeld bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that this is a ſin much to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which doth annihilate the ſauing power of the word of God, ſteale away the heart from the loue of heauen, &amp; the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6017:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>things of God: force the heart to the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring of the moſt foule temptations, and hinder the heart from attayning any part of bleſſedneſſe, yea plunge it into ſuch a multitude of curſes?</p>
            <p>Seeing then it is apparant that this vice is moſt enormious, and pernicious to the ſoule, let vs make ſome vſe of this point to our conſciences. Firſt then vpon this ground we may ſafely build an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all and euery of you, that you doe ſearch your owne hearts and liues, to find how farre this filthy ſinne hath found en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement there, when Ieſus Chriſt doth ſo preciſely forbid an euill, no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can deny, knowing his nature to bee inclinable to all euill, that it behooueth from ſuch exhortation, to take occaſion of examining himſelfe, how farre foorth he hath offended or doth offend in that kind. Chriſt would not giue warning of a fault to his ſeruants, if they were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſubiect to it, and if we be ſubiect to it, what can we doe leſſe than looke to it, if it be breeding in vs yea or no? So then, ſeeing you haue heard and perceiued the vileneſſe of this ſinne, I beſeech you euery
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6017:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>one not cenſure another, but to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his owne heart and life, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue diligently if the haue not been at the leaſt tainted and blemiſhed with the ſame, though not wholy polluted with it, which exhortation is ſo much the more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, by how much the practiſe of moſt men is more contrarie thereto; we come for the moſt part very ill affected to the word of God. When any ſinne is there diſgraced, and ſhewed to bee dangerous, we labour to poſt off thoſe ſpeeches to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other man and ſending the eyes of our mind abroad, which might haue beene farre better buſied at home; wee ſeeke a fit man to beſtow ſuch a leſſon vpon, chuſing rather to caſt it vpon any man, than to learne it our ſelues. Wee are too full of curteſie at theſe ſpirituall banquets. When ſuch a diſh as this is ſet before vs, namely the diſcountenancing or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending of a fault, wee lay that liberally vpon euery mans trencher, and no man almoſt will carue to himſelfe, becauſe that meat is indeede leſſe toothſome, though nothing leſſe wholeſome than the reſt. I beſeech you brethren that it may not bee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6017:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo with you in this point. Doe not ſay, (as it is an hundred to one that diuers of your hearts haue been buſied in ſaying.) if co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe be ſuch a ſinne, how ſhall ſuch a man and ſuch and ſuch a man doe, for all the world knowes them to bee coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous? Nay, heare not ſo idlely, the Lord ſpake to thee, and intended the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thy ſoule, and would haue thee ſay to thine owne lelfe, is couetouſneſſe ſo vile a fin, how carefull ſhould I be to finde it, and driue it out of mine heart, and my conuerſation? Doe not I practiſe it, do not I liue in it? let me looke narrowly, for as it is dangerous, ſo it is craftie, and will not appeare in it owne name, but (like a tray-tour that hath eſcaped out of priſon) will miſcall and diguiſe it ſelfe, and take twenty titles, and names, rather than that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it ſhould be called. Men are willing to cloake their ſins, &amp; to ſhift their hands of ſeeming to be naught, not being ſo. And as when the plague is rife, euery man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, though it be in his houſe, yet to keep it cloſe, and ſay it is any other diſeaſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will be ſome hindrance to be ſhut vp for it: So for this diſeaſe of filthy lucre,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6017:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>which as an infectious peſtilence hath ſpread it ſelfe ouer the world, into all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, townes, and villages, ſcarce any will be knowne to be diſeaſed with it, fearing the diſgrace rather then the danger. Some wold confine couetouſneſſe to rich mens houſes onely, as if it were not poſsible to be earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded, vnleſſe a man had much earth in poſſeſsion. But theſe men are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly deceiued about the nature of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, as themſelues might well perceiue had they but conſulted with the wiſe man, that ſaith, <hi>The ſluggard luſteth and hath nothing.</hi> A man may haue a ſtrong luſt to wealth, albeit he haue none of it. yea, though he be frozen vp in the cold dregs of idlenes, &amp; lazineſſe, ſo that he will not aduenture to ſet his foote vpon the cold ground for it. Nay, ſuch men are moſt deſperately coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, for becauſe their ſloth ſerues them not to take the ordinary paines for getting it, therefore their luſts driues them to hunt and ſeeke for it, in the ſecret and vnbeaten wayes of couſonage and villany. I would to God there were not a great number of ſuch ſlothfull luſters known in the world, perhaps alſo preſent in this place, whoſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6017:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>couetouſneſſe is no leſſe then other mens, out it is ouer-borne by ſome other luſt that is more then quarter maiſter with it. For this you muſt know, that this vice may be after a diuers manner in diuers men; in ſome it is the chiefe Lord and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, bearing rule and commaunding for it ſelfe; in others it rules as an vnder officer to another luſt, and is as I may ſay, the putueyer, or take for idleneſſe, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or prodigalitie. Sometimes it is whole maiſter, ſometimes halfe, ſometimes quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maiſter with theſe ſins before named; ſomtimes as ſeruant to all or ſome of them, for though theſe ſinnes cannot well agree among themſelues, yet they can all agree well enough againſt godlineſſe and pietie of life. Some ſcrape to keepe and looke vpon it; ſome ſcrape to ſcatter &amp; miſpend it; the one of theſe is as violent in his cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the other, and this ſinne is as hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yea, and more hurtfull to the parties ſelfe, to the Church and Common weale, when it is kept as a retainer to an other ſin, than if he had the chiefe-dome and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it ſelfe. Let not the prodigall, let not the ambitions, let not the ſluggard ſay,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6017:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>that hee is not couetous. I dare be bold to affirme, that if he had the grace and wiſe. dome to ſearch into himſelfe, hee ſhould finde this wicked vice as great a doer in his ſoule inwardly, and in his carriage out wardly, as in theirs, whom with great ſcorn, he diſgraces by the name of abſolute chuffes, and meere miſers: Send therefore I pray you brethren, each man his owne moſt ſerious conſiderations, as it were ſearchers into his heart and life, (and take an oath of them, to deale truly, and vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially) to ſee and obſerue, whether or no, he haue the infection of this peſtilent ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which alſo the words of Chriſt doe import, for hee ſaith, <hi>looke and ward your ſelues againſt Couetouſneſſe:</hi> as intimating, that there is no eſcaping it, if wee doe not looke to it. Now to the intent you may not be deceiued through errour in this ſearch, I wil ſtand a while to giue you ſome directions, which by following, you ſhall be ſure not to miſtake in examining and iudging our ſelues as concerning this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. To this end it ſhall be needefull for me to declare vnto you both;<note place="margin">What co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe is.</note> Firſt, <hi>What couetouſneſſe is:</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>What be the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6017:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>marks and tokens of it:</hi> which being known, it ſhall be eaſie for him that is not wilfully blinde, to paſſe an vpright ſentence of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore to ſhew what couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is: It is the dropſie of the minde, an horſe-leach humour after wealth, which euermore cryes giue, giue. It is that that makes the heart as a graue for money, or a deuouring ſepulchre, or a hell for goods, that will not be ſatisfied though you caſt very much into it. In few and plain terms, It is the deſire of hauing more than what a man hath already, that being ſufficient for neceſſary maintenance. If the Lord hath beſtowed vpon any man meanes enough to feede himſelfe, and thoſe that belong to him, with foode wholeſome &amp; competent, though perhaps ſomewhat courſe, as alſo to cloath himſelfe and his, with warme clothing, though neyther of the fineſt not in the faſhion, if his deſires doe not here ſtay themſelues, but ſtill cry more, more, this man is couetous, this ſinne is couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. He that would haue more then hee hath, hauing that which will ſuffice for his honeſt maintenance, though not in ſuch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6017:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>gay &amp; frolike manner as his fleſh deſireth, this is the couetous man, and ſo the word that is vſed by Chriſt ſignifies, <hi>vz,</hi> an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing diſpoſition: when a man ſo longeth for more then he hath, that he is ſtill rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take, (which cannot but follow) more then he ſhould haue. For couetouſneſſe &amp; true contentment, are one oppoſite to the other, as night and day, white and blacke, and therefore we may well know what co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe is, by the contrarietie which it hath with true contentment. Now the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth deſcribe true contentment in theſe tearmes,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.6</note> ſaying, <hi>If wee haue food and couering, let vs be ſufficed or ſatisfied with theſe,</hi> that is, let vs count that euen ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Theſe be the bounds which the Holy ghoſt hath made to hem and keepe in the vnruly deſires of men in reſpect of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, as it were wilde Bucks within a pale or parke Now if the wiſhes will not be ranged within theſe liſts and limits, but breake through them, or leape ouer them, to finde a larger walke, it cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the ſinne of couetouſneſſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. For the deſire that is in ordinate is this, that Chriſt forbids, and it is then
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6017:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>inordinate when it exceeds the rule, order,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> and precincts that God hath ſet and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for it, which are, to thinke the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things enough (and ſtop themſelues from ſtraying any further) when they will afford meat, drinke and cloth, ſufficient to content nature, in it moderate vſe to keepe ones ſelfe out of debt, and ſo bring him well to heauen, his iourneis end, as it were enough money to beare his charges in his trauaile towards God. Now if any man obiect againſt this and ſay, if couetouſnes be that which you haue deſcribed it to be, where will you find a man that hath it not, where can one be brought quite free from it? To this queſtion I muſt anſwere. No where, not vnder heauen, not within the compaſſe of the whole earth, for this ſin as well as other is bred in our nature, and cleaues as faſt to the ſoule of euery ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> as his skin to his fleſh. Why? but may ſome man further obiect, is euery man then ſubiect to thoſe enormious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and hideous curſes, which you before ſhewed to follow vpon couetouſneſſe? I anfwere, in no ſort, but alone thoſe men in whom this ſinne is ſuffered to be with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6017:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>allowance, is yeelded to, and followed. In ſome men as I ſhewed you before, this vice is as a ſoueraign Lord; in others it rules vnder ambition, and prodigalitie, in both theſe, all the bad effects named before, wil certainly follow, all the curſes denounced are to both theſe ſorts of men certainely due. In other ſome it is as an vnwelcome gueſt that intrudes himſelfe, it is like a bad tenant that is often warned to goe out, and will take no warning, it is not ſuffred to haue commaund, but it is ſtriuen againſt, reſiſted, complained off, and hath many a ſupplication put vp, and many a ſuit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced againſt it, in the court of heauen, for vſurping in an other mans right. To ſuch it is exceeding cumberſome &amp; tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and doth them meruailous much an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance, but yet it can neither produce thoſe vile effects, nor bring in thoſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible curſes. In a word, ſome haue it, and doe beware and take heed of it, as a diſeaſe that is applyed with medicines. Theſe it moleſts, but kils not. Others haue it, and neuer ſuſpect, feare, nor take heed of it, as a diſeaſe that a man careleſly lets go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out medicining: to theſe it is not ſo toyle-ſome,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6017:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>but more dangerous; for it ſlayes their ſoule, by bringing forth thoſe bad ſtuits before named. And thus as plainly as I could, I haue ſhewed you what coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe is in the very nature of it, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered without reſpect of the degrees thereof.</p>
            <p>Now I come to ſhew you the markes and tokens of it<note place="margin">The ſignes of it.</note> which was the ſecond thing I promiſed, to the end men might knowe themſelues, by which a man may alſo ſee in what meaſure or degree this ſin is in him; for if theſe things be found in his life, rarely and ſeldome, then coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe hath ſome ſecret and vnknowne allowance, through the deceitfulneſſe of his heart; but it is not wittingly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully maintained: if they doe appeare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ordinarily, then couetouſnes rules there, and is by him fauoured, loued, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto, and obeyed; it is Lord of his ſoule, though perhaps he be ſo full of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie as not to ſee or confeſſe it. And indeed it is a thing very needefull to ſhew theſe ſignes plainely, becauſe when out of our euill will we cenſure other men, we call them extreamly couetous, vpon theſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6017:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>grounds which will beare no ſuch accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation or action. As namely, if they bee painfull in their callings, if they haue more dealings in the world than our ſelues, if they will not giue at what time we would haue them, or ſuch like. But when in our fond ſelfe-loue wee are to ſpeake of our ſelues, wee will not dare to conclude, wee are very couetous, no not vpon the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt grounds and ſureſt proofes.</p>
            <p>To returne therfore to the point, There be 4. ſure and infallible ſigns and marks of this vice, which do as certainly proue it to be in the ſoule, as the yelow haire in the law did the leproſie, and as the carbuncle doth the plague The firſt of theſe is carking &amp; caring,<note place="margin">1. Carking</note> which is a note moſt eaſily ſeen and ſelt in men of lower place; for as ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes haue their diuers ſigns, in diuers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, ſo have alſo ſins in diuers condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and eſtates, diuers marks to knowe them by. Now this carking is for men of meaner eſtate, principally to try themſelus by. He that doth grieue &amp; moleſt himſelfe for the feare of want and miſery to come hereafter (for that is a proper deſcription of carking, it is ſorrow conceiued vpon the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6017:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>doubt and ſuſpition of that need that may come) the man I ſay, that doth ſo vexe and trouble himſelfe, is in that degree coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous that thus grieued. For the affections of our heart, are in their ſeuerall working ſo ioyned and linked together, that the working of ſome will not appeare, but vpon the precedent working of other. No man can inordinately ſorrow for feare of wanting that in the future time, which hee doeth not inordinately deſire for the preſent time. And for this cauſe our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, where he intends to ouerthrow couetouſneſſe, both in this Chapter, in the ſequell of his ſpeech, as alſo in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. fals vpon the matter of carking, and dwels much vpon that, ſaying: <hi>Care not what you ſhall eate, what you ſhal drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 6.25.34.</note> 
               <hi>and what you ſhal put on:</hi> and after, <hi>care not for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> bringing alſo many reaſons to that purpoſe, as wel ſeeing, that this ſin and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes doe alwayes goe hand in hand, in the poorer ſort chiefely, and ſometimes alſo in the wealthy: and that thoſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are of force to beat down the one, are alſo fit &amp; able to ſubdue the other too. And therefore alſo in the Parable,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6017:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>hee calleth couetouſnes by the very name of the <hi>cares of this world:</hi> becauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it is ſtrong, there it doth encum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the heart, and peſter it vp with a throng and multitude of moſt noyſome carkings.</p>
            <p>So then, if any man doe find himſelfe to ſtand ſo diſpoſed in minde, that hauing enough for the preſent time, yet he doth eat vp his heart, breake his ſleepe, diſquiet himſelfe, and turne into gaule, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort which he might haue in his life, by this vnprofitable and ouer-reaching thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: Ah how ſhall I doe if a deere yeere come? how, if I haue ſo many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? how if I liue till I be ſo old, or till I be lame or blind? ſure I ſhall ſpend all, I ſhall conſume all, I ſhall be vndone, I ſhall die a beggar, and come to great want and extremitie, and ſuch like terrible dreames: if any man I ſay ſtand thus affected, theſe things doe moſt rankly ſauour of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe: this vice playes the Lord and Tyrant in that mans ſoule, when he that is not aſſured of life till to morrow, nay, that ought to be ready to depart this life before to morrow, wil thus turmoile him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6017:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>with fruitleſſe and vnprofitable feare about that which his dreaming conceit tels him may befall, many a day, nay, many a year after (ſo not ſuffring himſelf to be free from a burthen, when he may, becauſe hee feares he ſhall not be free when he would) this man is moſt notoriouſly and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently couetous, and ſo muſt knowe himſelfe to bee, whether hee bee rich or poore.</p>
            <p>A ſecond note of couetouſneſſe, is nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardice,<note place="margin">2. Niggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice. Pro. 11.14</note> which is the fault which <hi>Salomon</hi> points out, when he ſaith; hee that ſpareth more then is fit. When a man is ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary of his wealth that hee cannot ſuffer a graine to be diminiſhed from the heape hereof, with any willingneſſe, no not then, when good, iuſt, and reaſonable cauſes doe require expence, when hee keepes his wealth to feed his eye, and ſaues his money to looke vpon, this is a fit that proceedeth from the deſiring of earthly things ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, and doth plainly declare an exceſſe of that humour. This the wiſe man ſets out, when he ſaith;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>There is an euill ſeene vnder the Sunne, a man to whom God hath giuen riches and treaſures, but hee hath not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6017:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>the power to cate thereof.</hi> This neereneſſe, &amp; immoderate ſauing, ſhewes that a mans ſou, e hath the dropſie, and that not alone when it grows to ſuch extremitie, as a man will pinch and depriue his owne perſon, and his wife, children, and ſeruants of thoſe comforts and benefits that hee might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, but euen then alſo, when a man is pinching towards the poore, and ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſted, that hee will not part with a part of his ſubſtance for the reliefe of thoſe which are in neede and neceſsitie, by him (which is indeede the true end, why God giues to one man more abundance, to an other leſſe) euen this hardneſſe, I ſay, to the poore and needy, doth prooue a man to be very dangerouſly couetous, though hee doe neuer ſo liberally, yea, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ouer-liberally beſtow vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; of which we haue a cleare proofe in the words of the Apoſtle, that ſaith; <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath this worlds goods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.17</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeth his brother want, and ſhutteth vp his compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him?</hi> That man, you ſee, that is ſo much giuen to holde and keepe, as when God calleth for it to releeue the diſtreſſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6017:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>comming as it were to borrow in and by them) he will ſay him nay, and turne him away emptie, or poorely ſerued, the loue of God doth not dwell in that man, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhew he may make; and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the loue of this world hath taken vp the holt of his heart, I doe not meane, (ney ther doth the Apoſtle) that he which giues not to euery vagrant rogue, or idle begger which comes to his doore, or meets him in the way, may preſently be termed vnlouing, and couetous: Nay there be two ſorts of poore; Gods poore, whom his hand croſsing them any way, hath brought to want, though they be laborious, and thriftie: and the diuels poore, vpon whom their owne idleneſſe, riote, and ſinnefull courſes haue forced neceſsitie: now for theſe laſt, vnleſſe they will ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to labour, and liue honeſtly, they ſhould be relieued with puniſhment and correction, and helped out of their ſinne, not maintained in it, by abuſiue mercy, or rather fooliſh pittie: but the former ſort of men, are thoſe whoſe caſe wee ſhould pittie and tender, as our owne, and therefore both open our hearts in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6017:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>compaſsion, and our purſes according to our power in liberalitie, to ſuccour and to helpe them. Gods poore muſt haue God almes, and for thoſe that in ſuch caſe can goe ſlincking, and trudging away, not extending their charitable contribution to the refreſhing of their bowels, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting their hearts that are preſſed with want, they muſt either giue the Apoſtle the lie, or confeſſe, that the loue of the world hath choked the loue of God, and of their neighbour, in them; yea when ſoeuer any needfull thing doth require vs to bee at ſome coſt and expence, either for the maintenance of Gods worſhip, or of the common good, as in publike ſeruices, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the like, but chiefly for works of mercy, then to mutter and grudge, and murmer and pinch, and hang backe, and complaine; is a certaine ſigne of an heart greedily diſpoſed towards earthly things; he that thinkes himſelfe ouercharged by ſuch expences, is certainely ouercharged with worldlineſſe. As he is prodigall that ſpends when the Diuell and his luſts call for it, ſo he is couetous, that ſpares when God and good vſes call for it.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6017:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The third note of couetouſneſſe,<note place="margin">3. Too much buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the world.</note> is to clog a mans ſelfe with too much outward buſineſſe, and to proſecute theſe earthly affaires ouer eagerly. When a man fals in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that ſinne which. <hi>Salomon</hi> forbids ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.4.</note> 
               <hi>Toyle not thy ſelfe to be rich:</hi> then it is ſure that he hath caſt his eyes vpon that which is nothing, that is, ſet his deſires o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-ſtrongly vpon thoſe outward vanities that haue no true ſubſtance in them. If any man for get the rule of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31.</note> that bids vs vſe this world as if wee vſed it not: and fall to ſuch immoderatenes in his dealings, as if he had neuer heard of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter world to prepare for: it is an vnqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable truth that hee deſires the things of this world more then he ſhould doe. Now then any mans buſineſſe is ouer-plentifull and exceſsiue, when the multitude thereof doth hinder him from the carefull &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant performing of all or any of the good duties appointed by God, for the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne, or his families ſoules. For the Lord hath compoſed man of two parts, the one a body which is fading and mortall, to liue here for a few dayes, and then yeeld to the ſtroke of death, and of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6017:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>corruption: the other a ſoule incorporall, ſpirituall, immortall, which cannot die, nor ſuffer corruption. And the Lords will is, that a man liuing here in the body, ſhould make all carefull, wiſe, and godly prouiſion for his ſoule, that that departing hence out of the body, may not be caſt into the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of eternall vengeance (which are prepared for ſuch as in this life vſe not all good diligence to eſcape them) but may rather enioy its portion in that euerlaſting and vnſpeakable bliſſe, which is alſo made ready for all them that doe conſtantly and with honeſt hearts vſe the meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame. And the meanes of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this happines, are faith &amp; repentance, and the continual encreaſe of theſe graces, by praying, reading, and meditating in the word, and good conference daily, as alſo hearing the word preached when occaſion is offered, and ſanctifying vnto the Lord for theſe vſes euery ſeauenth day. For the former of theſe, are to the ſoule of him that hath a true liuing ſoule, as I may ſo tearme them, daily repaſts and meales wherewith his inward man is ſtrengthened and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, growing daily from grace to grace:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6017:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>the latter, that is, the celebration of the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, is as I may ſay, a ſolemne feaſt day, and a great banquet for the ſoule, wherein all bodily labours ſo farre as mercy, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and comelineſſe will permit, being ſet apart, the ſoule ſhould haue libertie after a more then ordinary manner, to ſolace and delight it ſelfe in God, and feede vpon Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in the word and Sacraments, &amp; other holy exerciſes, that it may grow fat, &amp; well liking in all graces, and chiefely faith and repentance, the two principall graces.</p>
            <p>Now theſe being the meanes of Gods owne ordaining to attaine ſound grace here, and glory hereafter, dayly to pray, read, and meditate, and conferre of good things, &amp; weekly to ſanctifie the Sabboth, hee that doth ſo ſurcharge himſelfe or his family with outward buſines, that he hath not leiſure daily to performe the daily du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and weekly, that weekly dutie in ſuch conſcionable ſort as God doth require at his hand, for a purpoſe ſo profitable and moſt excellent, cannot denie that he loues the world too much; being that he ſeeketh not, as Chriſt commands: firſt, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, but firſt the worthleſſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6017:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>things that this earth can afford, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that which is the true and proper end of his being here; that is, to get grace and ſaluation, employes himſelfe too much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that which was but a ſecondary end, and to be done onely by the way, ſo farre as might be helpfull to the former, and no further. Euery man will yeeld that hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires earthly things inordinately, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires them more than eternall life: and it is as certaine, that he rather wiſheth wealth then eternall life, which ſuffers the meanes of attaining that, to ſhoulder out and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude quite, or elſe driue into a very narrow corner, &amp; ſmall roome, the means of attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this: for the deſires rule the actions, and that a man longeth moſt for, which hee moſt labours for. As he that ſuffers hawkes, hounds, and vain, though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues lawfull paſtimes, ſo to deuour his time, that he hath little or no leiſure for the performing of the fore-mentioned religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duties; is conuicted before all vnparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Iudges to be a louer of pleaſure more than a louer of God: So hee that ſuffers buying, ſelling, bargaining, reckoning, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing, and any ſuch buſineſſe lawfull in it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6017:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſelfe, but vnlawfull in the immoderate vſe of it, to rob him of leiſure for the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, muſt needs be condemned to loue wealth more than God, by the verdict of any man that will ſpeake the truth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his conſcience: and therefore bee it noted as a ſure rule, that euery man is in that meaſure couetous, that ouer-worke-ſome and laborious about worldly things, and in that meaſure ouer-laborious, that he ſuffers the plenty of theſe things to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw him from the conſcionable, conſtant, and holy performing of better things, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more directly to a better life.<note place="margin">4. Vniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of which.</note> Now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fows the laſt note of couetouſnes, and that is vniuſtice, or the vſing of iniurious and indirect meanes to get wealth. For muſt it not needes be yeelded, that hee deſireth wealth too much, which will dig to hell, &amp; fall downe to the diuell for it? And what elſe is it, but a falling downe to the Diuell for it, when a man doth put the regard of obedience to God, of charitie to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, of honeſtie in himſelfe, behinde the reſpect of enriching his eſtate; to al which things, doth he not manifeſtly prefer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that wil do wrong to win it? God forbids
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6017:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>wrong, charitie, honeſtie, and euery mans conſcience forbids it, onely the Diuell and lucre commaund it: Is hee not worthy to be called a money-ſlaue, and a ſlaue to the diuel, that wil diſobey all theſe, to ſerue the deſire of being rich, for is not euery man his ſeruant to whom he doth obey? And doth he not obey lucre abiectly, that will rebell againſt the moſt high Lord, and the conſcience his officer for theſe things ſake?</p>
            <p>So then euery man is ſo farre forth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous as vniuſt in his dealings.<note place="margin">1 In gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> Now all thoſe practiſes are vniuſt and vnequall, which be not conformable to two generall rules ſet downe in Scripture, that by them we might ſquare out al our particular acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The firſt is, to do to euery man as we would haue him do vnto vs. Not as we out of our diſordered &amp; diſtempered paſsions ſomtime be content to haue another deale with vs, ſo we may deale with them; but what in the true ſentence of our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> grounded vpon due and deliberate conſideration of the things we would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue of being done to vs, that wee muſt doe to our neighbours: ſo that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thing a man would condemne in his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6017:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>iudgement, not in his paſsions, being offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to himſelfe, that is wrong and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if he offer it to another.</p>
            <p>The ſecond rule is,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.13. 1 Cor. 13.6</note> 
               <hi>to ſerue each other in loue: for loue ſeekes not it owne thinges:</hi> meaning only without regard of another, but doth ſo equally and indifferently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider another with it ſelfe, that it would not profite it ſelfe with this endammage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; therefore whoſoeuer is wholy poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with ſelfe-regards, and hath his eye ſo fixed vpon his owne aduantage, that he cannot looke vpon another man with any euen regard of him; this man in all ſuch dealings walkes iniuriouſly, becauſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably, and ſhalbe condemned (though not by the ſtrict law of humane iuſtice, yet by the perfect rule of Chriſtian charitie) for a wrong doer. And by theſe 2. rules wiſely applyed to each ſeuerall action, it wilbe eaſie to ſpie out vniuſtice, though it hide it ſelfe vnder neuer ſo faire and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable pretexts. But wee ſhall not haue ſufficiently preſſed this ſore, if wee deale with it alone in ſuch generall termes, wherefore it is our purpoſe to ſpeak more particularly thereof, and leauing theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6017:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>practiſes that are of all men condemned as odious and vile,<note place="margin">2. In parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of ſuch vniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as is found.</note> and practiſed alone by the vileſt men in corners and in darkneſſe (ſuch as are ſtealing, robbing, forgerie, and all manner of couſonage, ſo termed:) we will ſpeak of thoſe which haue been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in the world vſually, with more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and in the Sun. ſhine; yea and ſome of them perhaps alſo defended, as if they did not deſerue the cenſure of vninſtice. And becauſe the things be many wherof we muſt ſpeake, we will ranke them into certaine heads, according to the nature of the ſubiects in whom they be moſt often found, for the reliefe of our owne and your memories. Some wrongfull actions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are found in miniſters of iuſtice, ſome in miniſters of the Goſpel, ſome in tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſome in landlords, ſome in all men without reſpect of their ſeuerall callings; of all which, we will ſpeake ſomewhat in order, and briefly to the intent that by them, euery man may (as we hope, euery Chriſtian man profeſsing religion will) ſearch himſelfe to the quicke, and vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially. Firſt then, for miniſters of Iuſtice, (by which name I terme all thoſe that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6017:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue any thing to doe in the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of publique equitie) in them vnleſſe they be carefull,<note place="margin">Miniſters of iniuſtice</note> there will be found very often three notorious points of wrong through the deſire of gaine. There firſt is briberie, or the receiuing of gifts,<note place="margin">1. Taking a gift.</note> though it be from the innocent, to haue hearing and iuſtice. For a bribe, is any gift taken by him that hath to deale in matters of iuſtice, of thoſe which are to come vnder his cenſure, whether for matters penall or capitall, whether they be offenders, or not offenders. And therefore the holy Ghoſt hath flatly forbidden to them the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of any gift at all:<note place="margin">Exod. 29.8</note> and in more then one or two places, hath cryed out againſt thoſe that loue gifts, and take gifts A gift of this kind is a thing of very ill name and note in the writing of the Spirit of God, who ſhewes his anger, ſaying: <hi>Fire ſhall deuoure the houſes of bribes. Iob.</hi> 15.34. This doth euen as it were build a neſt for vniuſtice and falſhoode, wherein ſhe may come with allowance, hearing, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, to lay all her ſubtill and craftie deuices and tales, for the foreſtalling of a true narration, that might elſe cleere a caſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6017:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>to the full. This fils vp the eare with the earewaxe of partialitie, that trueth cannot haue liberty with approbation to ſhew her minde and ſpeake for her ſelfe, vnleſſe ſhe vſe a golden earepicke firſt: and therefore God himſelfe ſaith,<note place="margin">Exo. 23.8.</note> 
               <hi>That it blindes the eyes of the wiſe:</hi> let a man haue neuer ſo good skil and knowledge in the law and matters of Iuſtice, if he ſuffer this duſt of a bribe, to bee ſcattered in the eyes of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this will ſurely follow, his eyes will (as I may ſay) water and twinckle, and growe worſe and worſe, till at the length he can ſee nothing, but becomes as blinde as a mole or bat. And indeed this kind of gaine muſt needs in Gods account, be as ſtolne goods, for the party receiuing the ſame, hath no manner of right or intereſt into it. For if the man that giues it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, to the knowledge of the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, he ſhould haue his cauſe heard and ſentenced aright, euen for his innocencie ſake, though he gaue nothing: If the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate know him to be nocent, a world of goods ſhould not keepe his ſinne from being made knowne and puniſhed: If the magiſtrate doe not yet know either his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6017:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>innocencie or faultines, he ſhuld not make himſelfe blind with a blinding gift, before he come to looke vpon the cauſe. And if any thinke that the will of the giuer doth transferre right to him that takes in ſuch caſe, he muſt knowe himſelfe to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſo thinking, for it is not a pure and voluntary will, but forced, becauſe hee knowes the humor of the man to be ſuch, that he will not doe right vnleſſe he be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to it. Euen as a man is willing rather to giue this purſe to the purſe-taker, than to venter his life or lim: ſo is he to giue a bribe to the bribe taker, rather than ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture his cauſe: &amp; therfore I dare boldly I ſay, and the God of heauen will iuſtifie my words, at the laſt day, that a theefe hath as much true right to the money that hee takes by the hye way, as the magiſtrate to the gift that he takes euen of the innocent party for a day of hearing, or the like: yea though it come not immediately vnto his owne hands, but be giuen to the wife, or ſonne, or ſeruant, or friend, by his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or allowance; which is but a little more cleanly conueiance of a bribe. Should Iuſtice be made as an hackney, that ſtirres
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6017:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>not out of dores but for hyre, or as a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenarie Souldier,<note place="margin">1. Peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting iuſtice or reward.</note> that will not draw his ſword but for his pay? A ſecond thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to this calling, is peruerting of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for a reward, which is a thing diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the former; for a man may bee ſaid to take a bribe, though hee paſſe true ſentence, &amp; do iuſtice for it: but this that I ſpeak of is worſe, when a man will goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt equitie for wages ſake, and this the ſcripture doeth alſo plentifully condemne in many places. If the iudge for ſomething that he hath already receiued, or hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenanted, or hopes to receiue hereafter, for him or any by his procurement, wil find a knot in a ruſh, &amp; condemn the cauſe which hee ſhould maintaine, but maintaine that which he ſhould condemne; or if thoſe that are to plead and declare matters in that truth which they ſee in them, will for an ouer-abundant fee, ſet a faire colour vpon a falſe cauſe, &amp; paint ouer a lie with ſhews, that it may ſeeme truth, (as by conceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome circumſtances &amp; the like) to delude right; (which is, to call euill good, and good euill; light darknes, &amp; darknes light, a thing that the holy Ghoſt cries wo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6017:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>vpon, whatſoeuer the wit of a couetous man can ſay, to make it ſeeme lawfull,) or when other officers that haue the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or helping to execute orders, will for a peece of mony find out delayes &amp; ſhifts and deuices, (as for example, fruſtrating or changing the order or decree, in ſetting it downe, and twenty ſuch other waies that I know not, but their conſciences can tell of that practiſe them, and God doth alſo ſee) all to ſhield and defend the wrong doer from the verdict that equity hath paſſed againſt him; theſe, and euery of theſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, to peruert iudgment for aduantage ſake, are notorious and palpable wrongs, and ſuch as euery man would condemne and abhor, if they were offered to himſelf.</p>
            <p>A third action of vniuſtice on ſuch, is Extortion,<note place="margin">3. Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> which alſo the lawes of the Land doe forbid, when hee that hath his allowance alotted him for his paines, in ſuch meſure as is thought by the law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, (which alſo hee may very lawfully and iuſtly take, ſo that hee performe his dutie for it,) when ſuch one I ſay wil doe nothing, or as good as nothing vnles this fee bee doubled or perhaps trebbled, or
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6017:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>perhaps will take fees on both ſides, one to ſpeake, another to hold his peace, or ſpeake nothing to the purpoſe. This is vile vniuſt dealing, the eye of nature can ſee it, the eye of grace can abhorre it, this is to take that which is none of ones own. If any preſent haue or doe offend in theſe or any of theſe points, or any like to theſe, be it knowne to him, that hee liues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly and couetouſly, and theſe actions ſhall ſtand vp before God and the world at the laſt day and witnes againſt him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; thou didſt harbour this couetouſneſſe which Chriſt condemnes, thou art the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man which the ſcripture ſaith can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not goe to heauen.</p>
            <p>Now come wee to ſuch vniuſtice as is found in miniſters of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">2 In Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their couetouſneſſe, for God and man would cry ſhame vpon vs for partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, if wee ſhould not taxe this ſinne in men of our owne coate, as well as others; ſeeing all the world can teſtifie, that it findes harbour in them alſo. Now the firſt ſinfull and vniuſt courſe vſed by Cleargi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, is called Simony,<note place="margin">1. Simony.</note> when a man buyes a Church-liuing, he ſhewes himſelfe to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6017:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſerue couetouſnes in the ſumme, not God, becauſe he comes in rather by the help of money than by the calling of God. And not alone is this ſinne then committed, when men be ſuch bunglers, in managing their matters, that the law will catch hold of them, but then alſo when there is Art in ſinning, &amp; as we ſay craft in daubing, when the man that is deſirous of liuing, doth not come with a downright bargaine, for feare of law: nor ſaith; Sir, if you will be my friend, and helpe me to ſuch a benefice or promotion, I wil giue you ſo much mony, or yeeld you, or your yonger ſon, or your ſeruant, or friend, ſo much commoditie out of it, and ſo forth. But eyther in great good wil, (to his own preferment. I meane not to the patron) will ſend him ſome goodly gift, or elſe in good earneſt will lay ſome wager with him, purpoſing to looſe the wager, rather then, not win the liuing, or elſe we ſell him too good a penniworth in ſome thing, taking farre leſſe than it is worth, or buy ſomething of him, for much more then it is worth; or vſe any ſuch like tricks to delude law and couſen equitie: theſe deuices be alſo Simony, as odious in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6017:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>truth as the moſt plaine kinde of bargaine that can be made; vnder which rancke alſo comes for the moſt part, that vſuall courſe of buying aduowſons, for hee that buyes, muſt ſell, that euery man knowes, or elſe hee muſt liue by the loſſe, which men of this ſtampe, will ſeldome or neuer doe if they can chuſe. And in this fault, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron hath as great a ſhare as the Miniſter, yea, and greater too; becauſe the fountaine of the fault is in him; for if he would giue freely, no man need to buy it, &amp; he ſhould be able to diſcerne that ſuch a couetous harpie as is willing to pay for it, were in no ſort fit for the place, &amp; therefore ſhould in no ſort beſtow it vpon him, much leſſe ſet it to ſale to him, being that the lawes haue committed this care to his charge, not that he ſhould make a commoditie of it, for then it had bin fitter to giue it vnto poorer men, whoſe low ebbe did require to be filled vp by ſuch helps, and not as it is commonly, to the Lords of the places, whoſe reuenues if they were not groſly eyther couetous or prodigall, might well ſuffice them: the lawes, I ſay, haue laid the care of preſenting a fit man vpon him,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6017:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>not becauſe he ſhould paſſe it ouer to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for mony, or himſelfe make a gaine of it; but becauſe hee ſhould doe faithfull and profitable ſeruice vnto the Church &amp; Common-weale, in prouiding a man of good parts and competent gifts, as being thought the moſt of abilitie to iudge of ſuch an one, &amp; to ſeeke him out. Here ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a couetous Patron, and a couetous Miniſter, muſt be content to diuide the fault betwixt them, and endure to be called vniuſt and worldly, for making bargaine and ſale of the maintenance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>A ſecond fault and that farre more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious in men of this ranke, is,<note place="margin">2. To feed themſelues and not the flocke.</note> when they doe feede themſelues, and not the flocke, through idleneſſe, or careleſneſſe, doe ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer driue the ſheepe of Chriſt vnto the greene paſtures, or the ſtil waters, that the Lord hath prouided for them.</p>
            <p>When I ſay, ſuch a thing as this is done, it is of all the particular vniuſtices which I haue named, or ſhall name, the moſt abhominable to God, &amp; ought to be ſo accounted alſo amongſt men. For the Church-liuings are, as it were, the reuenues
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6017:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Ieſus Chriſt, and his endowments, to be diſpoſed by him, and it is his order that thoſe ſhould liue of the Altar, not which loyter, but which labour at it and therfore thoſe that labor not haue no intereſt from him to eate of the fruits, &amp; if they preſume to doe it, they fill and fat themſelues with ſtolne and ill gotten goods, which though they taſt ſweet in the mouth ſhall prooue grauell, yea worme-wood, yea, poyſon in the bowels. Now the labour that the holy Ghoſt requires at the hand of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel, is apparantly ſet down in Scripture, that no man can without wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes be ignorant of it.<note place="margin">Mat. 29.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>Go preach and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe all nations, teaching them to obſerue all things that I haue commaunded you;</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>woe vnto me if I preach not the Goſpel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 9.16 2. Tim. 4.1.2.</note> And againe, <hi>I charge thee before God, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Ieſus, who ſhall iudge the quick and dead at his appearance, and in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preach the word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon. Reproue, exhort, rebuke, with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</hi> An other part of his function is,<note place="margin">Tim. 2.15.</note> to reade the word vnto them publikely, as the Leuites did in former time, for God forbid we ſhould diſallow
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6017:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>this ſo profitable &amp; comfortable an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,<note place="margin">Act. 8.31.</note> becauſe many content themſelues with this alone. And another part is, to pray with them, and be as it were their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner to God in publike. Another is, to adminiſter the Sacraments of baptiſme &amp; the Lords ſupper. An other part of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, in priuate to ouerſee their waies, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting the weak, ſtrengthening the feeble, &amp; admoniſhing the vnruly, that ſo he may giue a good account to God for them, who will require them and their bloud at his hand. Now he that feeds vpon the liuing, &amp; doth not in ſome good meaſure ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to do thoſe things which God calleth vpon him to doe, hee is a loyterer, hee is an hireling.</p>
            <p>To take Gods wages, and not doe his worke at all, or elſe negligently, is a great and a curſed wrong, and ſo much the more hurtfull then other wrongs, by how much it doth more neerely &amp; dangerouſly touch the ſoules of men, who muſt (for any thank that is due to him) periſh for euer; when the meanes of God appointed to ſaue men, is not vſed by him the Miniſter, whom God ſets as a watchman, and puts in truſt with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6017:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch a waightie imployment. And all ſuch men ſhal haue the bloud of the parties pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing through their default required at their hand. It behoued me to haue my no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils ſtrangely ſtopt with a poze of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, if I had not ſmelt theſe practiſes to ſauour rankly of couetouſnes, and to haue had my mouth baſely muſled with partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, if I had not freely reprooued it: and therfore if any in the miniſtery be preſent, that vſeth theſe courſes to enrich himſelfe by, be it known to his face, yea, to his ſoule, that theſe ſins ſhall ariſe before God, with the aſſent of his owne conſcience, and with a loud and ſhrill voyce, proclaime in his eares, to his ſhame and confuſion, if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not. Thou haſt harboured this coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe that Chriſt bids beware of, thou art the couetous man, that canſt not inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the kingdome of God.</p>
            <p>Now let vs proceed to Tradeſ-men,<note place="margin">3. Tradeſ-men.</note> who are occupyed in buying &amp; ſelling, &amp; ſhew how indirect courſes are incident to their place, as teſtimonies of a worldly heart.</p>
            <p>The principall are theſe.<note place="margin">1. Falſe waights &amp; meaſures.</note> Firſt, to vſe falſe waights and meaſures, that is, when the waights and meaſures, by which they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6017:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>buy or ſell, eyther are not of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, extent, &amp; height that the law requires they ſhould, and they are by cuſtome taken for, or if they be, yet there is couſonage vſed in applying of them, by iogging, ſhaking, turning and ſwift conueyances, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not name, but mens hearts can tell that vſe them, and ſo alſo can the Lord that ſeeth the heart. Now ſuch, the light of nature Ioaths, and God condemnes with a woe, and ſaith,<note place="margin">Pro. 11.1.</note> 
               <hi>falſe waights</hi> (and they be as bad as falſe that are falſely vſed,) <hi>are an abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord,</hi> and hee would not abhorre them, if they were not vniuſt.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, to ſell, corrupted, falſe, ſophiſticated, and inſufficient wares,<note place="margin">2. Inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient wares.</note> ſuch as are not in qualitie as good, or in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the ſame, that the ſeller would haue the buyer to take them for; which ſinne is moſt grieuous in Apothecaries, becauſe there it may alſo haue a ſpice of murther, mixed with vniuſtice, and for ſuch dealing as this, ſeeing euery man will exclaime and grudge againſt it, being offred to himſelfe, we will ſeeke no other proofe but his own confeſsion, to condemne it in himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The third is, to engroſſe, or foreſtall,<note place="margin">3. Ingro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</note> that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6017:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>is, to buy vp any commoditie before hand, when it is, or might be cheape, to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing of a future dearth, that ſo hee may make his gaine at his pleaſure afterwards. It is lawful to buy vp the ouer-plus of any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, I mean the reſidue, when mens turnes are ſerued in the time of plentie, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did; that a man may haue it to helpe the common weale in time of dearth, with ſome good and moderate gaine to himſelfe alſo; but the ingroſſer in ſtead of laying vp the ſuperfluitie of plenty, to preuent and helpe a dearth; doth hoord vp the ſtore of plentie, to procure one, which is to cut the throat of the common weale for his owne aduantage ſake: And therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pro. 11.26</note> 
               <hi>Him that hoords vp corne the people ſhall curſe.</hi> And ſeeing the ſame reaſon is of all things in their degree, I may ſay the ſame of all, the ingroſer ſhall be accurſed, &amp; he could not be ſo, if he were not vniuſt.</p>
            <p>A fourth thing iniurious in ſuch men is,<note place="margin">4 To abuſe the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of men.</note> play and prey vpon the neceſsitie or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of men, eyther in thruſting a thing vpon them for much, that a mans ſelfe knowes to be worth little; or in getting a thing from them for little, which he knows
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6017:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be worth more; becauſe they know not the thing, or elſe muſt needes haue it, or part with it. In a word, any exacting of too much, or giuing too little, chiefly when we abuſe the ignorance or the neede of our neighbour to this end; is to ſerue ones ſelfe in ſelfe-loue, and not his brother in loue, and therefore is vniuſt.</p>
            <p>Now if any aske how I can informe their conſciences concerning the encreaſing or diminiſhing of the price, I will referre him to the firſt generall rule fore-named, and wiſh him to aske as little, &amp; offer as much as himſelf, if he were in the ſame caſe, wold willingly, not by compulſion haue taken of him, or giuen to him, all things conſidered in due manner; to deale otherwiſe then ſo, is to deale iniuriouſly and vnrighteouſly.</p>
            <p>The fift to this condition of people,<note place="margin">5. To get away ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans cuſtome or bargaine.</note> is to get away another mans cuſtome by odd tricks; as for example, to offer and ſell him a very cheape penny-worth, yea, cheaper than can be afforded for once or twice, which a man purpoſeth to fetch out at ſome other time, afterwards, when he hath gotten him in, and ſuch like, and ſo to take an other mans bargaine out of his hand, is
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6017:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the ſame kind for the buyer, that this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for the ſeller: for ſuch dealing no man can take in good part, when it is done to himſelfe, and therefore the law of nature and God both, doe condemne it, as naught and vnequall.</p>
            <p>The laſt vniuſtice in men of this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is to liue by wicked trades,<note place="margin">6. Vſing vnlawfull trades, or abuſing lawfull.</note> which ſerue directly to the ſupporting of vice and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: as for example, by keeping di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing houſes, filthy houſes, bowling alleys, &amp; ſuch like places of helliſh reſort, which are as it were the diuels houſes of office: the hote and vnſauory ſteames wherof, do prouoke heauen, and defile the world. And ſuch is alſo the abuſe of lawful trades to the ſame purpoſe, as in Painters or the like, in making idolatrous or filthy pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as fit inſtruments to prouoke ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or bodilie fornication. So of Stationers, in ſelling and diſpercing filthy and laſciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pamphlets: and here the common ſin of Vintners and Ale-houſ-keepers be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely taxed, in that they permit brutiſh creatures worſe than ſwine, to ſit and ſwill, &amp; waſh away their reaſon &amp; diſcretion, til the houſe be made a ſink of filthy vomiting
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6017:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>the baſenes of which men, &amp; loathſomenes of which practiſe no man wold ſuffer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his doores, but that the ſweetnes of gain makes him ready to giue welcome to the blackeſt fiend of hel, that ſhal come with a ful purſe, and a lauiſh hand to mispend the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now theſe, or all, or any of theſe, if any tradeſ-man preſent vſe, be it known to him without doubting, that they ſhall all ſtand vp to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation in the preſence of God, and cry out vpon him, ſaying; Thou doſt entertain this couetouſnes that Chriſt forbids: thou art the couetous man ſo much condemned in the word of God, whoſe ſoule cannot be ſaued if it ſo continue.</p>
            <p>And now muſt I go on to ſpeak of thoſe euilsin land-lords,<note place="margin">4. Land-lords, as</note> that hauing much them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſet or let grounds, or liuings, or hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which doe proclaime the ſoueraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; dominion of couetouſneſſe in them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, to racke Rents,<note place="margin">1. To rack rents.</note> and exact immoderate and exceſsiue fines, I meane not the requiring of more rents than haue beene accuſtomed in former times, to bee paid; for it is doubtleſſe lawful to improue land; but I meane, lifting them to ſuch an
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6017:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>high &amp; vnreaſonable rate, that the tenant ſhall not liue any thing comfortably ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, but in extremitie of toyle and want, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forced eyther to vſe vnlawfull ſhifts, &amp; baſe niggardice, or elſe to daſh himſelfe vpon the rocke of penury and need. This is to grinde the faces of the poore, and it is that ſin of oppreſsion, ſo much ſpoken againſt in men of this place, by Gods word. Now if any man ask what rule may be ſet downe out of Scripture, as a ſure direction for the prices in ſuch caſes? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, let him ſet himſelfe in the Tenants place, &amp; what he would then giue (volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, not vpon conſtraint and extremity, all things laide together according to the quantitie of the thing, that, and no more than that, muſt he take, &amp; not ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be tranſported by the ſweet tongue of euery flattering ſeruant, and vnſatiable deſire of getting money, to fling away vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his pleaſures, or elſe augmenting the reuenues for the next heyre. He that will not make himſelfe a patern of his dealing to others, is condemned by his conſcience to deale not righteouſly.</p>
            <p>The ſecond fault of Land-lords is, to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6017:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>burden and lade their tenants with carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages &amp; like ſeruices, more then was agreed vpon in the couenant betwixt them,<note place="margin">2. To bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with carriages &amp;c. more then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying him for it as an other man will do. As for example, to carry ſtone and tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for his building, to plow land, to inne hay and corne, to fetch fewel or fire-wood, to remoue houſhold ſtuffe, and all this <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi> The Land-lord may not challenge this priuiledge ouer the Tenant, to make him work for nothing, where he is not tyed by the condition of his leaſe, nay, nor then neither, if it be vnreaſonable, and tend to his vndoing. For this the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> durſt condemne in a King; and therefore I need not feare to condemne it in a land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, of what place ſoeuer. For ſo ſaith he of the King of Iudah, <hi>Iehoachim</hi> ſonne of <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>Woe to him that builds his houſe by vnrighteouſneſſe, and his chambers without equitie,</hi> and wherein ſtood this lacke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie? <hi>he vſeth his neighbour</hi> (or makes him ſetue) <hi>without wages, and giues him not for his worke.</hi> You ſee this ſharply reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Prophet long agoe, as voide of equitie, that no man may diride it as a toy of our owne head.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:6017:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A third vniuſtice among Land-lords, is by fraud or might to depriue the tenants of any part of their duties, as of ſome greene, or common, or wood, or ſuch like, that appertaineth vnto them: this is that which the Prophet condemnes by the name of coueting a field, and taking it by force. Now theſe courſes ſpecified, or any of the like kind, if any Land-lord preſent accuſtome himſelfe vnto, be it plainely ſpoken vnto him alſo, that theſe his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall make appearance, and giue in euidence againſt him before the great Iudge, ringing this grieuous out-cry in his eares, and ſaying; Thine heart hath lodged the forbidden ſinne of couetouſneſſe, thou alſo art that couetous man, that ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing cannot be ſaued. Now we come in the laſt place to ſet forth the lewd practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that are common to all men, without reſpect of their ſeuerall places, and theſe are foure.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Promiſe breaking.</note> to make deceitfull promiſes, or to breake promiſes and couenants. When a man lookes to his profit more than to his truth or honeſtie; and therefore will make his bargaine or promiſe in ſuch ſlippery
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6017:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>or doubtfull words or manner, that ſtill he will find ſome euaſion to pull out his owne necke, when hee hath made another to ſerue his turne, as by pleading that hee meant not ſo, or ſo; or that ſuch and ſuch a thing ſhould be vnderſtood; or that he hath forgot it, or ſuch like: albeit he had wit enough to expreſſe his meaning fully, and plainely, if he had would, and needed not to haue reſerued ſomething for after-claps. Yea, and hath ſufficient memorie, if hee had ſufficient honeſtie to beare it in minde too, but chiefly when he will come to a plaine refuſall, being deſtitute of all ſhifts and excuſes, this is monſtrous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, which the blind light of nature can ſee well enough and challenge. For an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, much more a Chriſtian, ſhould ſtand to his lawfull word, though to his owne hinderance, &amp; that according to the true meaning and intent, expreſſed in his promiſe, and vnderſtood by the party to whom it was made.<note place="margin">2. Vſurie.</note> A ſecond notorious vniuſtice is vſury. When a man makes a gaine of lending, and binds the party bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing, without conſideration of his gaines or loſſes, to repay the principall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6017:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>with aduantage. For whereas there be three ſorts of men that vſe to borrow, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poore men, whom neceſsitie driues to it, or vnthrifts, whome prodigalitie driues to it: or ſufficient men, that hope to make a commoditie of it: It is apparant by the confeſsion euen of thoſe that would ſeeme to ſay ſomewhat for this vſurie, (as if it were not a ſinne ſimply) that it is wicked to lend on vſe to the poore needy borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,<note place="margin">Deut. 15.7.8.9.</note> for God hath flatly commaunded to lend vnto him freely; and for the vnthrift, it is alſo certaine that hee ſhould not be lent to at all; for that is to feede his iſſue with ill humours, and to put a ſword into his hand wherewith to deſtroy himſelfe; and thus the vſurers moſt accuſtomed and greateſt gaines are cut off. Now for the third kind of men, of them to exact gaine vnconditionably, not reſpecting their loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or getting, is altogether againſt the law of charitie and equitie both. For the light of nature will not ſuffer any to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this principall of equitie: that he which will haue part in weale, muſt alſo haue part in woes; and hee that will diuide the ſweet, muſt alſo diuide the ſower: hee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6017:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>that will take of the good ſucceſſe, muſt alſo take of the bad: and the light of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will not ſuffer him that hath any of it, to deny this principall of charitie; that Chriſtians muſt ſerue one another in loue, and not themſelues alone in ſelf-loue; both which principals are directly contrary to the very trade of the vſurer, for he makes ſure for himſelfe to haue a part onely and infallibly in the profit, and therefore ſerues himſelfe alone, and alſo his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and for this cauſe the vſurer is ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that cannot come to dwell in the mountaine of God, which bee ſhould not be, were hee not vniuſt. So then, the vſurer whether he doe it plainly or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, as men haue a thouſand policies to couer their ſinne in this reſpect, muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the imputation of liuing by wrong and iniurie.</p>
            <p>A third vniuſtice in any man, is, to withhold dues from thoſe to whom they belong, as debts, wages, and the goods of orphanes, and ſuch things as haue been giuen for charitable vſes, and the like. Theſe be ſo openly euill, that I ſee not how any man can open his mouth with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6017:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>any ſhew, or colour to iuſtifie them. When a man will pay his hireling nothing, but keepe his owne from him by fraud or put him off with ill words, and poſt him away from time to time, or make him becauſe he is his tenant, &amp;c. take one or two pence in a day, leſſe than others giue, or pay him very grumblingly, who could brooke ſuch dealing, and not ſay, fie vpon it, it is ſtarke ſtaring wrong? So when a man hath wherewithall to pay his debts, in ſome meaſure at leaſt, and yet will breake and not diſcharge them ſo farre as it will goe, or when being a rich man, he ſends away the creditor all to be rated and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with ill words, and empty of money, but laden with reuiling ſpeeches; yea, though he haue to diſcharge it: what man doth not loath to meete with ſuch vſage to himſelfe? but chiefely when the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe childe or widdow haue not the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bequeathed to them, and committed in truſt to a friend, reaſonably, fully, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily paid in vnto them, this euery man ſees to be bad dealing. In a word, to retaine any part of anothers due, is indignitie.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Salomon</hi> hath ſayd, <hi>With-hold not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6017:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>the goods from the owners thereof.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3.27 To liue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenths, chiefely not proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Gods worſhip.</note> Another vniuſtice of this kind in lay-men, is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsing of tenths, or church-liuing, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially without any care, to haue the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the miniſtry faithfully and ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged. For not to ſtand vpon that queſtion, whether tenths be due by Gods law to the miniſter, (which yet I thinke) might probably and ſufficiently be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, euen againſt a cauilling and wittie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iector, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaying, that he which is taught in the word, muſt make him that teacheth him partaker of all his goods;<note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> doth thereby intereſt the miniſter into ſome portion of his peoples ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Now ſeeing none other part was euer aſsigned him, either by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the lawe of God, but this, doth not it probably at the leaſt follow, that euen vnder the Goſpel this is his due? but I ſay not to diſpute this queſtion, we haue another reaſon to conuince apparantly, that the tenthes cannot, by that true right which will hold good in the courts of conſcience, and of heauen, be detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the miniſtrie, without ſome full requitall other way; for whatſoeuer
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6017:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath once bin giuen &amp; conſecrated to the maintenance of Gods worſhip, and the true religion eſtabliſhed by him, that is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted into the perſon of God, or intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled vnto Ieſus Chriſt (as I may ſo ſpeak) who wil neuer acknowledge any fine, and hath this royall prerogatiue, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is once his, the ſame is alwaies his; and whatſoeuer is giuen to him can neuer be taken from him: neyther is there any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing againſt him, ſeeing he hath ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperiour, nor law aboue him, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can forfait no right;<note place="margin">Pro. 20.25</note> ſo that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deſtruction to deuoure holy things and after the vow to require. Now that theſe tithes were giuen &amp; deuoted by men well diſpoſed to the maintenance of the true worſhip of God, euen before groſſe and heriticall popery had ouer-clouded the face of the world, is a thing that I thinke no man will or can deny. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the concluſion follows ineuitably, that they be Gods ſtil, and not to be beſtowed any other way than in his ſeruice. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lay-men therefore as ſerue themſelues with Church-goods, deale vniuſtly with God and mens ſoules, and cannot eſcape
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6017:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>the blot of worldlineſſe, if knowing this, they reforme it not. The laſt vniuſtice that I wil name as common to all ſorts of men, is gaming in hope of gains. Neither let the the gameſter except that his riotous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour cannot come within the compaſſe of couetouſneſſe, for hee doth therefore venture vnthriftily that hee may get more vnlawfully, and his manner of gaining is moſt palpable wrongfull. He takes that to which he hath no right at all that might make it his. He pleads none other title but that he won it, that is, plaid better than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, or perhaps not ſo, but onely caſt the lot more luckely, and all the wit vnder heauen can neuer ſet a colour of lawfulnes vpon this plea. I muſt haue his money, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I plaid better than hee, or threw the dice more happily. If he alleadge the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant betwixt him &amp; the party that play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with him, that is nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Foreuery lawfull couenant is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing of ſome lawfull right that was in nature before the couenant, as the ground thereof, which hee cannot name any, and therfore the couenant is vnlawfull, &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not giue him lawfull poſſeſsion of any
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6017:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing. If he flie to the mutual will of them that play, let him not vrge that will, but the ground of it; which is to get another mans goods, and therefore it is wicked, &amp; cannot be the foundation of a iuſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Indeede all will transferring right, muſt eyther bee free-will (and then the thing ſo paſſed ouer is free gift, of which nature he will not acknowledge the thing that he wins, neither can he call it ſo if hee would) or elſe will grounded vpon ſome lawfull and equal conſideration, which the gameſter cannot for his life make ſhift to name any: and therefore this will that hee ſpeakes of, is either none or naught, and ſo he plaies the theefe with another, when he winnes, as with himſelfe when he looſeth. And whatſoeuer man hee may be in preſence, that accuſtomes to any of theſe laſt named things for his riches ſake, let it be certified to his heart, that theſe things ſhall condemne him before the Lord and ſay; Thou alſo doſt yeeld to this ſin of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, and thou art the couetous man that ſo continuing, cannot enter into life eternal. Thus haue we at the laſt brethren, ſhewed you both what couetouſneſſe is,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6017:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the notes of it, <hi>viz,</hi> carking, niggar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, greedineſſe in dealing, and all vniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: whether in Magiſtrates, Miniſters, Tradeſmen, Land-lords, or any men: Be you exhorted now to deale plainely and faithfully with your owne ſoules, and by theſe notes, ſearch, try, and examine your owne hearts, that you may know your own eſtate truely in this behalfe: and be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, God is not mocked. What wil it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile thee to ſay, I am not couetous, if God will ſay thou art, ſhal not his word &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſtand? And let this be the firſt vſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> let me be bold to reproue thoſe men among you, that haue their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences vpbrayding them with this ſinne, by any of the forenamed ſignes. I cannot be thought to intend a perticular inuectiue againſt any mans perſon, my diſacquaintance with this place &amp; all in it will ſufficiently defend me from this imputation, ſeeing I know ſcarce any of your faces. Nay, beloued brethren, it is the ſin that I deſire to make odious &amp; hateful to all men, &amp; not any mans perſon whatſoeuer: &amp; as for thoſe that cannot but plead guilty of this fault, they ought to ſubmit their harts to the ſharpeſt reproofe,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6017:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>and be content by a bitter medicine to be healed of a poyſonfull diſeaſe. I know that that is very true which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith; The couetous bleſſeth himſelfe, none more, and his hand hath gotten wealth; no man muſt finde fault with him, that were ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie; but by how much hee is more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to himſelfe, by ſo much muſt vvee with more loudneſſe and vehemencie, ſound foorth the trumpet of Gods venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt him: and let him heare it to his affrightment, if his hard heart would feele any thing, that hee is as loathſome in Gods eyes as any, &amp; as ſubiect to his curſe as who is moſt ſubiect. And whereas the prints, and footeſteps of this enormious crime, are apparant almoſt euery where in euery condition of men, I muſt bee bold in Gods name, to pronounce a woe againſt their ſoules, and tell their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which will alſo beare witneſſe to my words, that they are as abhominable in gods eies, as the world is precious in theirs. Ah what a ſhamefull thing is this, that a man profeſsing the goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, which would bee eſteemed his faithfull ſubiect, ſhould yet harbour in his heart, &amp;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6017:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſerue in his life, this vile traytor which Chriſt hath preſcribed long agoe, &amp; wold haue exiled &amp; baniſhed, yea, &amp; quite cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of the world, chiefely out of the hearts of all that call themſelues by his name, Chriſtians? Is this agreeable to the profeſsion of Chriſtianitie, to haue thine heart thus wedded to the world, ſtil earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, earthward, alwayes looking to the things that are below? haſt thou ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Ieſus Chriſt? Doth he deale ſo vnlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly with thee, as not to giue thee better, more laſting, and comfortable things to delight in? or dealeſt thou not moſt vnlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly with thy ſelfe and him, that hauing an offer of that moſt precious treaſure, ioyeſt rather to lade thy ſelfe with this thicke clay? With what words ſhall I ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently condemne &amp; diſgrace this folly? it is madnes, meere madnes, and worſe then the worſt lunacie that is. When wilt thou learne to be aſhamed of thy ſelfe, and to bluſh in conſideration of thy childiſh dealing, yea, thy wicked demeanour in this reſpect? Did we euer learne any ſuch thing in the ſchoole of Chriſt, or in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? did his conuerſation euer ſauour of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6017:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>couetouſnes? yea, did he not willingly chuſe to want all things almoſt for our ſakes? to teach vs in his owne perſon, that pouertie is no ſuch matter, and wealth no ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable things as wee make them in our conceits? Muſt wee not then needs blame our ſelues, that haue rather choſen to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our owne corrupted affections, &amp; the ſinfull faſhion of the wicked world, than his moſt wholeſome direction, and moſt holy patterne? What muſt Chriſt ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, when thou ſhalt appeare before him in another world? or art thou ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an Atheiſt, as not to dreame of ſuch a day? muſt hee not ſtrike thine eare with a chiding and vnpleaſant voyce, &amp; ſay; Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall and vnfaithful ſeruant, would neither words nor deeds worke vpon thee? I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; thee to beware of couetouſnes; I commaunded thee firſt to ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, &amp; the righteouſnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; I commanded thee not to labor for the things that periſhed, but for the things that endured to eternal life. Mine example alſo taught the ſame things, thou neuer readeſt of any carking in me, though I had not an houſe to put mine head in, thou
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6017:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>neuer heardeſt of any niggardice, toyling, or vniuſtice in all my life: yea, I did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne theſe things as trifles, not worth looking after, &amp; refuſed a kingdome, when it ſhould haue been thruſt vpon me. Canſt thou be ignorant of theſe things without wilfulnes, or knowing, neglect them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rebellion? and yet wilt thou call thy ſelfe my ſeruant, when thou regardeſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deeds nor words of mine? What could the Heathen haue done more, or worſe? Say it had neuer beene tolde thee, that there was a God, a Heauen, an eternall Kingdome; ſay thou neuer haddeſt heard, or ſuſpected any happineſſe to be found, beſides wealth, and outward abundance, couldſt thou haue bin more cold, &amp; drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in ſeeking the one, more feruent &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in purſuing the other? could my word profit thee no more, to diuorce thee from the loue of this world, to perſwade thee of the baſeneſſe of earthly things, &amp; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect excellency of heauenly things? Goe then and take thy reward with worldlings; Conſider brethren, what a moſt terrible word it will be, to be bid then depart from Chriſt, to the diuel &amp; his angels, whether we
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6017:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>will or nay; becauſe we departed from him wilfully before to the world, and its doung and droſſe: and know you that as ſure as God is true, ſo you ſhall finde it at the laſt day, a couetous man ſhall not goe for an honeſt man, or good Chriſtian more than a whore or theefe. Flatter not your ſelues with being neyther whores nor theeues, harlots and adulterers: theeues &amp; robbers ſhall as ſoone come into the kingdome of God as your ſelues, and yet you know that ſuch ſhall neuer come there.</p>
            <p>But if the couetous man diſdaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with ſuch foule companions, and think himſelfe wronged, in that ſuch loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome men are equaled with him; Let him heare what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; <hi>This you know, that no fornicator, nor vncleane perſon, nor couetous man, which is an idolater, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the Kingdome of God and of Chriſt.</hi> Lend thine eare and be affrighted, O thou worling, is this Scripture, or is it not? Art thou an Atheiſt to denie it, or one of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> fooles to deſpiſe it? But yet for more aſſurance heare againe the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaying; <hi>No fornicator, nor Idolater, nor Adulterer, nor wanton, nor Buggerer, nor
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6017:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>theefe, nor extortioner, nor couetous man, nor drunkard, nor rayler, ſhall inherite the kingdome of God.</hi> Loe thy companions and fellows, &amp; know what thou art in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, doth hee not tie thee, as a malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, in the ſame chaine, with thoſe whom all the world cries ſhame vpon, and whom thy ſelfe doeſt loath and ſcorne? wilt thou not ſee thy ſelfe alſo to be a limme of the diuell, becauſe a darling of the world, and as farre from heauen as ſhee that liues in the ſtewes, and he that robs by the high way-ſide?</p>
            <p>Now if perhaps any will ſtand out and ſay he is not a couetous man, let mee call God, and the world, and your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and your deedes to witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a number of you, that you be ſo in extremitie. Doe not many of you carke, and care, and pine your hearts almoſt with needleſſe doubtings, and ſuſpitions of neceſsitie to be hereafter, when your owne being is vncertaine, euen for a day, and are you not couetous? Are not many ſo pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and miſerable, that no mercie, no liberalitie, no bountie can bee ſeene in their liues, and the time is to come that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6017:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>euer they did voluntarily beſtow any thing for the reliefe of the needy, or if any thing, it comes out pinchingly in pence, &amp; two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, when God hath giuen it in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abundance to doe more good, and yet are you not couetous? Doe not a number lade themſelues ſo burdenſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with worldly dealings, that God and Religion, and a better life, can finde no place in their ſerious conſiderations; and that eyther they neuer pray, reade, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, or elſe ſo drouſily, and coldly, and ſhortly, as if they thought euery houre tenne, till they were returned to their worke; yea, doth not the world enchroch vpon the greateſt part of the Sabboth, in many mens tongus and hands, that would be thought Religious, and are you not yet couetous? Is not all vniuſtice rife? Aske your owne hearts you Magiſtrates, and anſwere in ſecret, but in truth: Doe you not take gifts? Doe you not often force your Conſciences to thinke what they ſhould not, and your hands to doe what they ſhould not, in defending, ſentencing, writing, executing any thing for a reward? and will you denie that you are couetous?
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6017:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>queſtion with your hearts, ye tradeſ-men, will they not tell you that you doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe, exact ſophiſticate, and vſe falſe weights, meaſures, and words, and perhaps alſo more darke trickes, that Gods eyes ſee, and can tell of, and are you not coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous? Doe not you Land-lords rack your rents, burden your tenants, defraud them, oppreſſe them, grinde their faces: and will you ſay that you are not couetous? Doe not ſome of you Miniſters, come in by Simonie, and being entered, loyter and neglect a flocke or two, feeding the Lords ſheepe more careleſly than you would be content to haue an heard of your owne ſwine fed, and are you not couetous? Are they not common amongſt all ſorts, to lie, couſen, and breake promiſe and ſhift, to giue your money to vſurie, to withhold the goods of others in your hands, to liue by Church-liuings, and care not for the Church, &amp; are you not couetous? I would to God brethren, that theſe things did not cry out in the eares of the Lord of hoſtes, and the ordinary practiſe of them, like the roaring of many waters, complaine vnto him of our earthlineſſe. Yea I would
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6017:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>we did not complaine too much one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another; and he that practiſeth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe in one thing, ſeekes to make himſelfe ſeeme honeſt, by exclaiming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt as bad pranckes in others. Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates cry out of tradeſ-men, and they of Magiſtrates; they of Miniſters, the people of Land-lords; almoſt euery man of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for this ſinne, and will you not ſee it in your ſelues, and be aſhamed of it? Let me diſcharge a good conſcience, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, tell the couetous man, I meane him in whom any of theſe things do beare ſway, that he is a counrerfeit Chriſtian, an hollow-hearted proteſtant, and a diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling profeſſor, that makes gaine his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and his wealth his God: and know thou againe, that heauen is ſhut againſt thee as faſt, as againſt the fowleſt ſinner that the earth holds. Hearken O couetous man, whoſoeuer thou beeſt, and ſee, that thou ſhalt ſurely die in this thy ſinne, if thou doe not ſpeedily amend it: the loue of the world will pull thee down to hell, vnleſſe thou make haſt to caſt it off, and be thou alſo among the other crue of preſumptuous ſinners, accurſed in the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6017:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>name of the Lord. But ah my brethren, doe we delight in threatnings, or is it our pleaſure to rake in the wounds of your ſoule, with the naile of a reproofe? nay we deſire to heale them, which we could not doe without wiping forth this feſtred wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and for none other end ſhew you the danger of your eſtate, but that you may get out of it; and therefore for the laſt vſe, doe beſeech you all, that ſee what is amiſſe to reforme your ſelues.</p>
            <p>There be two degrees of couetous men, ſome ſo fully poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of the world, that God is their enimie, and they his, and ſo they cannot poſsibly bee ſaued. Such are thoſe whoſe cuſtome it is to runne thorow thicke and thinne, to get riches, and who liue in the ordinary practiſe of knowne euils for wealths ſake; namely, thoſe which I haue before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or ſome like to them. If thou be one of theſe, to thee the curſe denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced doth certainely belong; and ſhall cleaue to thy ſoule ſo faſt, that neither men nor Angels ſhall ſeperate the ſame, vnleſſe thou doe ſpeedily amend. Pittie thy ſelfe miſerable man, pittie thy ſelfe,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6017:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>leape not into hell, it is a place of torment, both fearefull and eternall. Caſt not thy ſelfe into the flames of damnation. Why wilt thou die, and haſt been warned? Is all the world worth one ſoule? Ah make not ſuch an hard bargaine, but haue compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon thy dying ſoule. Bewaile and confeſſe thy ſinne before the Lord, leaue and forſake thine vniuſt courſes, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſires. Be it ſufficient that thou haſt been all this while a ſlaue to the world; now lay hold vpon this liberty of the ſons of God: ſhake off this yoake of Sathan; weane thy ſelfe from the breaſts of the world, and caſt from thee the too much liking of thoſe things that are more baſe, than that an eternall ſpirit ſhould build it delights vpon them. But if I cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with this neere and abſolute world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, if he will needs be guilty of his owne damnation, &amp; refuſe to commiſerate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, what remedie, who can help him that will not help himſelf? let him periſh. And let me with more hope of ſucceſſe, turne my ſpeech to the ſecond degree of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous men, ſuch as though they bee not wholy excluded the hope of ſaluation,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6017:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>becauſe this ſinne is not abſolute Lord of their liues, yet are hindred from many ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary comforts, and come into many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable euils; becauſe they be not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inough to purge themſelues of this vice. Of this kind are many profeſſors of true religion, that haue giuen ſome good teſtimony of their vprightneſſe and truth, and made good proceedings in the waies of God, which yet for want of ſufficient care to reſiſt &amp; reforme this fault in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, haue been ſhamefully foyled by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and drawne ſomtimes to moſt vniuſt and diſcommendable courſes, ſuch as the wicked world hath euen taken notice of; and as I may ſo ſpeake, hath ſhowted and howted at them, glad to take any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore much more reioycing that ſo iuſt a cauſe of euill ſpeaking hath been offered. It is an outcry of the world, that thoſe which would be accounted moſt forward profeſſors of religion, thoſe that doe ſeeme to make ſo much account of preaching and ſermons, and ſo forth, euen theſe are as hard, as vniuſt, as couetous in their dealings, as the worſt of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. And ſurely brethren, though the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6017:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>world (willing to report the worſt of things) doe vſe a tricke of rethorique in aggrauating, yet it cannot be denyed that your liues hath giuen matter inough to worke vpon; It is a true complaint of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that make great ſhew of religion, that though they bee not as couetous as the worſt, yet they be too notoriouſly coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous; and the ouer-abundance of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill weed, doth diſſauour all the graces and vertues which are or ſeeme to be in them. Why wilt thou if thou feareſt God, ſuffer thy ſelfe to be ſo baſely carried away with the deſires of theſe things, that here-hence thou ſhouldeſt run into courſes of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as make thy profeſsion euill ſpoken of, as open the wicked mouthes of clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous men againſt thee, as renders thy name, a white or marke, for all thoſe that are willing to caſt out the venemous darts of oblequie and reproch againſt the ſame; as giues wicked men occaſion to ſhelter themſelues from all reproofes by retorting thy bad actions in the face of the reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as make ſinners to applaude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their ſinnes, and thinke, though I make not ſuch a ſhew as ſuch an one, yet
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6017:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>he is as couetous, as I am otherwiſe faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Yea, as doe cauſe all good men and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf to receiue diſgrace, when they can ſay (though lyingly, yet badly enough, hauing the example of ſome ſuch to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend as euidence againſt all) that ſuch are all the ſort of you. I beſeech you brethren if any of you that feare God, haue beene ouerled with theſe earthly things, let him now ſee and conſider of theſe many and grieuous inconueniences, and ſee what the immoderate following of the world can yeelde him anſwerable to the loſſe of all thoſe comforts that his heart ſhould enioy if it were rid better of this ſin, and to thoſe good affections, and praiſes that he ſhould haue from good men, if he did ouer-come this ſinne, and to that freedome and ſafety from the ſcourge of the tougues of lewd men, that might come to him, had he not giuen them the aduantage againſt him, by vnmuzling their mouthes, with the too too groſſe practiſing of this ſinne.</p>
            <p>Now then conſider this with thy ſelfe, whoſoeuer thou maiſt be; Diſgrace thy ſelfe, diſgrace religion; diſhonor Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, cauſe wicked men to exult, thy
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6017:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>friends &amp; Gods ſeruants to be grieued no more. Do no more I ſay ruſh vpon all, or any of theſe inconueniences, through the too much dotage after theſe baſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible things. If I cannot preuaile with them that haue beene wholy worldlings, and altogether men of this earth, yet with thee that haſt ſome good things, ſome ſparkes of Gods ſpirit, ſome truth of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and hope of a better life, let me, yea, let God and Gods ordinance preuaile to make thee reforme thine heart and life, in this behalfe, in comming to this place, and lending your eare to Ieſus Chriſt, ſpeaking in his owne ordinance; you make a ſhew to intend obedience to his word, who by his ſpirit ſtands in the midſt of you ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching euery mans hidden heart; you make a ſhew of obedience, the ende of hearing is doing. Shew me that you were not hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrits in comming to the ſermon, let your liues ſpeake for you, that you did in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie preſent your ſelues before the Lord, and were neither fooles to come hither to no end, nor diſſemblers to come for a wrong end. I doubt not but euery one of your conſciences, which hath with any
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6017:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſonable attention hearkned, is, I am ſure it ought to haue beene ſufficiently conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the loathſomneſſe and vileneſſe of this ſinne; yea, and of our owne faultineſſe in it diuers wayes. Shew forth the fruite of the word, gaine a bleſsing, be doers, not hearers alone.</p>
            <p>Now you haue looked in the glaſſe of the word and ſeene the ſpots and ſtaines of earthlineſſe diſcouered, go home &amp; purge and cleanſe your ſelues of them hereafter. Be not like him that looks in a glaſſe, but waſheth not his face; be not ſo, but let the word of God be to you in power, caſt this monſtrous euill and the dregs of it out of your likings and your liues. But will ſome man ſay, is ſin ſo eaſily left? or can wee ſo ſoon preuail againſt it indeed, as you ſpeak againſt it? no but there muſt be ſome pains taken about it, and then I doe not doubt, nay, dare promiſe to a chriſtian ſoule, the victory againſt this ſin, &amp; that it ſhall goe downe the winde, and bee of the looſing hand. And that you may the better amend your ſelues in this matter, I will ſtand a while to ſhew you theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt what be the cauſes of couetouſnes:
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6017:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>Secondly,<note place="margin">The cauſes of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe are miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of God and of wealth.</note> what be the remedies againſt couetouſneſſe, which if any man will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply wiſely vnto himſelfe hee ſhall finde a meruailous cure, and that in a ſhort ſpace, wrought vpon his heart.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, the maine and principall procreant cauſes of couetouſneſſe, are two errors in the vnderſtanding or iudgement: For indeed ſuch is the nature of the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that they doe ſeldome or neuer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, but through the former faultineſſe of the mind. Seldome doth the deſire, or loue, or hatred, ouer-ſhoote themſelues, but through the deceite of the vnderſtanding part, that being firſt diſordered it ſelfe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders thoſe that are as ſeruants to it; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſtie to the worſt, and ouer-ſlow in the beſt actions. And in the perticular, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the deſire is inordinately and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully carryed after wealth, becauſe the eye of the minde miſtaketh it marke, in theſe two reſpects: Firſt, it doth not apprehend in God ſuch abundance of power and will to ſaue, helpe, and deliuer, as indeed there is in him, and euery man ſhould acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in him, and ſo the mind being by this falſhood driuen from the ſtrong hold of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6017:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>Gods name is faine to caſt about for ſome other place of defence, and then wealth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it ſelfe to helpe, as the bramble to the king ouer the trees, &amp; the mind ſtill daze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and iudging after the appearances of things, not after the truth, doth conceiue that riches are indeed able to helpe. Now vpon theſe two groſſe miſtakings, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that the deſire which is ready preſt to purſue that which is eſteemed helpfull and profitable, ſets forward it ſelfe, with all it might to purſue after wealth, and this is the originall of couetouſneſſe. So is this foule euill begotten of the minde; it is the darke and blind brood of an erronions and deluded iudgement. And both theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are laid open cleere enough before vs in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>The firſt in <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. where hauing warned vs of couetouſnes, he ſaith, for he hath ſaid, <hi>I will neuer leaue, &amp;c.</hi> By this coherence, ſufficiently intimating, that couetouſneſſe comes, becauſe one thinks God will not be ſure enough to him, but too quickly and lightly leaue him to himſelfe. And the ſecond cauſe Chriſt notes in this Text, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>for though a man haue much, his life
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6017:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſiſts not in his wealth:</hi> as if he had ſaid, you deſire much wealth, becauſe you think it can make you liue more comfortably &amp; ſafely, but indeed it cannot. You ſee now the true cauſes of couetouſneſſe. I know men are willing to make ſhew that this their deſire of wealth is of better paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but the truth is, it is as I haue ſaid, the baſe brood of ignorance and errour.</p>
            <p>Now come wee to ſhew the remedies of this ſinne,<note place="margin">2. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. 1 Apply the word to it in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</note> and how it may be conſumed out of vs: Firſt, there are foure remedies in all. The firſt is, to meditate vpon the word of God that forbids it. Applying the reproofes, and threatnings, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, againſt any ſin in the word of God to a mans owne ſoule, by ſerious meditation, is a common remedy againſt all ſins, and ſo alſo againſt this. The word of God is the ſword of the Spirit, ſeruing to keep out all luſts from comming with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vs, and to cut, wound, and ſlay them; to which purpoſe it is then effectuall, when it is weelded as it ought, by turning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and reproofes of it into earneſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt our ſins, &amp; ſtrong petitions for our ſelues before the Lord in ſecret.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6017:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Indeede lamentable experience driues vs to confeſſe, that the word of God is of litle operation in moſt men for God: &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is this? euen from their owne folly, that out of their ſinfull hollownes, will not lay it as a plaiſter to the ſores of the ſoule: but bee this ſpoken in aſſurance of truth, &amp; let the heart of euery godly man giue conſent to it, that whoſoeuer hee be which takes the word of God in any perticular matter, and alone betwixt God &amp; his own ſoule, ſtands to conſider, ſaying: Loe how plainly the Lord hath forbidden this ſinne, what ſharp reproofes he hath vttered againſt it, how great the danger is, that he hath threatned ſhall ariſe from it, why do I commit it? why do I liue in it? Doe I either not beleeue his word, or not feare his diſpleaſure? And then turning himſelfe vnto the Lord, doth earneſtly cry out againſt himſelfe, ſaying: Ah Lord God, how wicked haue I beene to break this thy law, and to endanger my ſelfe to thine indignation, and ruſh vpon thine anger ſo ouer-ventrouſly?</p>
            <p>Now Lord giue more wiſedome, more grace, ſtrengthen me to do thy will, which I ſee &amp; know, but of my ſelfe cannot obey:
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6017:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>whoſoeuer I ſay, doth in this or the like manner ſpread the plaiſter of Gods word vpon his own heart, let him count the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God but leaſings, if he finde it not able to heale any luſt, though neuer ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered and inueterate; to quell any corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though neuer ſo ſtrong and violent. Doe thus therefore brethen, for couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, we have ſhewed you ſufficiently, what an hurtfull and vnlawfull thing it is. Enter into thy cloſet as Chriſt bids thee; pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of theſe things; ſet downe your owne hearts with theſe reaſons, and conuince your ſelues of the wickedneſſe thereof, and accuſe your ſelues before God with indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt your ſelues, that are ſo baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enclining to this world, when the Lord bids the contrary; Yea, and beſeech him to ſtrengthen and ſanctifie your hearts now, that ſeeing his will, you may yeeld to it: and that theſe reproofes may be preſent with your hearts to controll them, and checke them ſharply, when they ſo offend, &amp; that it would pleaſe him to encline your hearts to his teſtimonies, and not vnto couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and hee that thus doth conſtantly day by day, or as often as occaſion is, let him be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6017:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>bold to promiſe to himſelfe, that the word will proue a word of life and power vnto him. It will knock off theſe clogs of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, from his ſoule, that his affections ſhal be no longer ſo fettered with them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond remedy againſt couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Get aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life.</note> is to labour for more and more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the fauour of God and euerlaſting life, through Ieſus Chriſt his ſon: and euery man muſt haue his happines and delight. And if any mans hart be not ſet vpon the true felicitie, it will be ſeduced by falſe; &amp; one guilded vanitie or another will ſteale it away from him: but let a chriſtian ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to make his calling and election ſure, and to be ſtedfaſtly reſolute of this, that God for his deare ſonnes ſake, pardoning all his finnes, wil beſlow eternall happines vpon him, &amp; cauſe him to raigne as a king with his Sonne, in a throne of immortall glory; where is no ſin, no ſorrow, no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nothing to grieue or vexe him; but the fulneſſe of ioy at Gods right hand for euermore; and the ſight and comfortable expectations of this eſtate, will ſo rauiſh his heart, and take vp his deſires, that this vile earth will appeare to be as it is, and he ſhal
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6017:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>be able out of his owne feeling to call it dung and aſhes, as the Apoſtle doth, not ſuffering it to cary the name of a treaſure in his eſtimation. Yea, and his ſoule from this maine ground will draw another conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of no leſſe force to beat downe the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of worldlines, ſaying; If God wil giue the fleſh and bloud of his ſonne to be the food of my ſoule, wil not he giue me bread and drink to ſuſtaine my body? If his loue were ſo infinit that he ſpared not his moſt beloued and onely begotten ſonne for my ſake, how ſhall he not with him giue mee all things? He that will ſaue the ſoule, will he not feed the body? will he deny droſſe, that gaue gold? will he ſay nay for a pibble, that ſo liberally ſcattered pearls? Nay ſure, if our Lord would giue Chriſt for vs, and to vs, for our ſaluation, it were madnes to doubt whether he will giue earthly things for maintenance, ſo farre as is good (and further what Chriſtian can wiſh them) for God is alwayes ſuitable to himſelfe, in all his dealings: Get good reaſons to truſt God with thy foule, and thou wilt neuer feare thy body and thine eſtate. Haue eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſtrong enough for heauen, and thine
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6017:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>heart will not deſire earth, and much leſſe doubt of hauing ſufficient therein.</p>
            <p>The third remedy againſt couetouſnes is, to conſider aduiſedly,<note place="margin">3. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well Gods tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> of Gods gratious promiſes abundantly made and written in his word to his ſeruants, euen for prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of temporall benefits: wee haue his word, yea, his deed, his teſtament ſealed and deliuered vnto vs in the preſence of all his Saints and Angels; wee haue his bond, vnder white and blacke, ſaying: <hi>The Lyons ſhall be hunger-starued, but they that feare the Lord ſhall want nothing.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine;<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10</note> 
               <hi>The Lord our God is a Sunne and ſhield, and no good thing will hee with-holde from them that walke vprightly.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine;<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.11</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is my ſhep-heard, I ſhall want nothing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 23.1.</note> And this the Author to the Hebrewes preſſeth, ſaying; <hi>Let your conuerſation be without couetouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.5.</note> 
               <hi>and be content with that that is preſent.</hi> Yea, but we cannot be content, we haue good reaſon to deſire more; For how if hard times and dangers ſhould come, who ſhuld then prouide for vs? Who ſhould prouide? Why, are you Chriſtians, yea or no? if no: ſtriue to be ſo firſt of all. If ye know that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6017:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>God is not ſo wretchleſſe a father, you are not left to ſhift for your ſelues, nor caſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to your owne prouiding. Nay, you haue one to care for you, and that for euer, if you can but beleeue his word. Hee, the God of mercie, the God of wiſedome, the God of truth, the God of power, the God of wealth, the maker and owner of all worlds, the God all-ſufficient, he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his word for your ſuretie. Wee giue much credit to a mans promiſe, and think we are in good plight if a wealthy friend, ſpecially if he be truſty alſo, doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to helpe vs. This is not man that may be changed, but the vnchangeable God: not man that may deceiue, but God that cannot lie: not man that may be hindred, but God whom none can reſiſt: not man that may die, but God that liues for euer. And he hath ſaid, I will neuer leaue you, not in age, not in ſickneſſe, not in a deere yeere, not in hard times, not when you be friendleſſe, not when the world is naught, and the dayes hard and euill; he will neuer leaue you nor forſake you; neuer caſt you off, nor ceaſe to doe you good. O faithleſſe and vnbeleeuing hearts, if we do not reſt,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6017:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>builde, and repoſe our ſelues, vpon a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſo plaine, ſo firme, ſo plentifull; and fooles and abſurd, if beleeuing this we wil giue our hearts to the world Heape wealth together whileſt thou wilt, it is not thine but Gods, he muſt giue it thee out of thine owne cheſt, as well as another mans. And if thou haſt neuer ſo little, he hath neuer the leſſe, and can giue thee out of another mans cheſt, as well as thine owne. What needeſt thou offend God, wrong man, and trouble thy ſelfe to get that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for thee in Gods keeping long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? and thou haſt it as much if it be in any mans cuſtody, as if in thine owne. But pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall children will not liue at their fathers finding, till their owne wayes make them teturne weeping home: and we are loath to ſtand to Gods ſimple prouiſion forſooth, it ſufficeth vs not, wee muſt haue more, though we peirce our ſelues through with woful temptations for it, becauſe we ſeeke riches more then his fauour. When will we cauſe our liues to witneſſe that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue God is true? yea, when will vve ceaſe to call him a lyer actually, by coueting for our ſelues, and not truſting on him that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6017:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>careth for vs. Thinke we on theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, haue them in a readineſſe, and when our hearts doe troubleſomely queſtion within vs, who ſhall helpe vs when we be olde, or in aduerſitie, if we doe not now ſcrape together? ſet them downe and ſay, God will care for me if he be true; and if hee be not, it bootes not to get wealth, for then the world and all in it muſt come to nothing, together with his truth, which is himſelfe.<note place="margin">4. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what wealth is to which care, mark.</note> Now the laſt remedie againſt couetouſnes, and as needfull as any of the reſt, is, to informe our ſelues truly as concerning the nature of wealth. For none can loue it but through ignorance, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, but through loue. Looke vpon it as it is in it ſelfe, without the paintings of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and our deſires wil of themſelues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it, &amp; as it wer ſcorn to be captiue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. Now the contemptiblenes of wealth will be manifeſt, if we ſet our ſelues wel to conſider of theſe things following. Firſt, what kind of men haue moſt of it. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how vncertain.<note place="margin">1. What men haue had moſt of it.</note> Thirdly, how vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Laſtly, alſo how hurtfull it is. For the firſt then, let the ſtories be asked both of holy writ and profane authors, &amp; let them
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:6017:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeak, who be the men, &amp; what haue they been which haue waded through the ſea of the world, in the greateſt and the talleſt veſſels, haue not many of them been the moſt brutiſh men, the verieſt beaſts, and the moſt loathſome &amp; abhominable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that euer breathed aire, or ſaw the Sunne, &amp; ſuch as a Chriſtian man cannot name without hating? <hi>Kaynes; Nimrods, Cams, Iſmaels, Eſaus, Saules, Ahabs, Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadnezars, Baltazers, Herods, Iudaſſes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels?</hi> And in other authours, <hi>Nero, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus, Heliogabalus,</hi> &amp; other monſters of men? Indeede I deny not, but good men haue alſo been wealthy, but that which is ſo common to good and bad, that for the moſt part, the worſt haue had moſt of it: cannot if God be the diſpoſer of things be the true treaſure. What is that that a wiſe man doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly caſt to dogs, but bones or carion; that he giues to ſwine, but draffe or huſkes; what is that God giues to ſuch as are worſe than ſwine, or dogs; but worſe I meane, more baſe than draffe or carion? Think we that the God of heauen is ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a diſpencer of good things, that hee would caſt pearls to ſwine, or good things
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6017:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>to dogs? Surely were there ſo much excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in theſe matters, as wee fooliſhly dreame of, they ſhould not bee flung to thoſe whom God hates, and purpoſes to fat as Hogs for the day of ſlaughter; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt vpon his children, whom hee doth intend to glorifie with himſelfe. God feedes them full with theſe things, whom he will throw to hell; thou maiſt be a rich man, and yet a diuell for all that; goe then and deſire wealth, if thou thinkeſt it yet the true treaſure.</p>
            <p>But yet further conſider wee how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable it is.<note place="margin">2 How vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable it is.</note> Take wealth as we meane it, for the ouer-plus of things neceſſary to competent maintenance, and you ſhall not be able to deny (ſet opinion aſide a while) that it is a thing of nought: Will you not yeelde that God is wiſe enough to call things by their right names, and to entitle euery creature after the true nature of it? Aske then the ſcripture the voice of God, what this gold and ſiluer, theſe lands, and linings, &amp; rich poſſeſsions, this god Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhould bee called? Will it not anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were <hi>A ſhadow</hi> ſaying:<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.6.</note> 
               <hi>Man walketh in a ſhadow, he troubles himſelfe in vaine, euery
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6017:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>man heapes vp, and knowes not who ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it.</hi> Will it not ſay, <hi>A flowre?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.24.</note> for <hi>all fleſh is graſſe, and the glory thereof as the flowre of graſſe.</hi> Will it not ſay, <hi>lies?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 62.9. Eccle 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>The chiefe men are liers.</hi> Will it not ſay <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitie?</hi> for <hi>All is vanitie.</hi> Wil it not ſay <hi>Nothing?</hi> as <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23.7</note> 
               <hi>Wilt thou ſet thine eyes vpon it, and it is not, it hath no being?</hi> Eyther challenge God of folly, or falſhoode, which hath called this wealth ſhadowes, flowers, lyes, vanitie, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or elſe yeeld that we haue been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in thinking better of it Wil we not ſee our errour, and confeſſe that wee haue beene couſoned as children, with gawdes, and now begin to truſt our fathers iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? But you ſhall ſee that it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe vilified with theſe titles, and if you will but lend an heart to iudge, as an eare to heare, you ſhall perceiue as cleare as noone day, that they be as vnprofitable as any ſhadow. What will you terme that, that can do no good, to ſoule, body, name, ſtate, nor keepe any euill from ſoule, body, name, ſtate, nor mittigate ſuch euils as a man is preſſed withall, in any of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects? Euery man will yeeld it may well be called a thing of nought, and cannot
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6017:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>well be called by a better name. Beleeue not ſhewes and conceits, and then be your ſelues iudges, if wealth, I meane ouerplus of maintenance, can doe any thing in any of the forenamed reſpects.<note place="margin">1. Soule, for getting good things of it</note> What is good for the ſoule, but faith, repentance, the ſpirit of God, the anſwering of our praiers, the pardon of our ſinnes, and the attaining of eternall life? And I pray you, can you buy theſe things for money? can you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe them with Iewels? or get them for exchange of goods? will God giue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to any man, if hee will morgage a faire liuing to him for it? Will he giue him faith, that can bring a rich Iewell, or a purſe of golde for it? or will he heare his prayers any whit ſooner in his need, that is clad in cloth of gold, and hath thouſands by the yeare, than if he went in meane apparell, &amp; had not twice twenty pound, nay twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pence yearely? or is there any commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of penance in heauen? or can we by a great fine anſwere for a fault? Indeed if any of you be ſo blockiſh, as to beleeue the palpable deceits of popiſh Rome, ſome of theſe things are ſet to ſale there, and there you may buy indulgences and pardons:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6017:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>but we know well enough that Rome and heauen ſtand a good way a ſunder, and they be not ruled by the ſame lawes, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil God ſtand to thoſe bargaines that the Pope makes for money. You haue all yeelded, now that for ſoule, money cannot bring any good to it. But what?<note place="margin">2. Body for the ſame reſpect.</note> cannot it profit the body more? Aske experience. Will wealth buy health? will it purchaſe eaſe, or a good nights reſt, or an houres ſleepe, or a good ſtomack, or any of theſe things that are leſſe then theſe? Anſwere what you know by proofe: will wealth buy theſe things? and what is the body the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it then? But yet perhaps the name may be more beholding to it.<note place="margin">3. The Name.</note> It will ſurely bring credit, and good eſtimation. Indeed here, if in any thing, the rich man magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies himſelfe aboue the poore, becauſe he takes himſelfe to be in better reputation. But here if in any thing he is moſt of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. I confeſſe it makes him think much better of himſelf, but neither God nor man doe thinke the better. Yea, God and good men thinke the worſe of him for this. If it come in by violence, oppreſsion, robbery, and vniuſtice, you will yeeld that no man
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6017:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath the better liking of one for ſuch wealth. But ſay that a man hath not waded through theſe filthy and ſtinking guzzels to get it, but haue come vnto it in the moſt cleanly manner, as ſome, but not the moſt doe, it ſhall be plaine, if any reaſon will rule vs, that it cannot get a good name or credit. For ſay, what will you call credit? to haue cap and curteſie, and a bended knee, and a few complements of behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our acted vnto your ſilken coate, or before your ſelfe it may be, or to be looked after and gazed vpon by the deceiued multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and to be followed by a great number of hangbyes that runne after you, as Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles after a dead carkaſſe to feede vpon you? Is this credit? is this eſtimation? to be crouched vnto as a little curre doth to a maſtiffe, to be ſoothed vp, and heare faire words, to be all beſprinkeled with court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy water euery day; in a word, to be ſtabd with the cut-throat kindneſſe of flatterie? If you call this credit, and if this be the good name you talke of, it is euen a fit thing to bee gotten with wealth, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable credit, an vncomfortable credit, an hurtfull credit, with vnprofitable,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6017:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>vncomfortable, and hurtfull riches.</p>
            <p>And if any man haue but a graine of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he will ſee that this is ſar from cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit or a good name. But if it be to be vvell eſteemed of in the hearts of men, to finde reuerence in their ſoules, to haue their conſciences commend one, and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man ſet him (as it were) in a good roome of the affections, and their priuate thoughts, to yeeld a good teſtimonie for him: If I ſay, this be accounted credit, as it is indeed, a man is neuer a whit the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to it for abundance of goods. That will make men fawne and wag the taile, as a curre vpon his maiſter that is at dinner, to get a bone, yea, and perhaps alſo to licke ouer his ſores, with a poyſoning, not an healing tongue (for in this a flatterer is ten times worſe then a dog; yea, he is a venim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthed dog) but behinde his backe, and in his abſence none ſhall be more readie to talke of his ſaults, to deride them, to blaze them, to diſgmce them, than he that crouched ſo much in his preſence, and did him ſo much (as you pleaſe to call it) cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to his face; yea, and in the middeſt of all this crouching, no mans heart doth
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6017:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>more loath, abhorre, ſcorne, and contemn him, than the man that is ſo ſeruile and officious becauſe of wealth.</p>
            <p>And this is all that wealth can procure for the name, but nothing vnder heauen can make the hearts of men to reuerence any, and their ſoules to haue in good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, yea and prefer him (in their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture iudgement) euen before themſelues. Nothing can doe this I ſay, but grace and vertue, true pietie, true holineſſe, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of conuerſation, to which money cannot helpe a man. A poore man that fares but reaſonably, and goes in ordinary attire, and cannot ſhew either money or lands of his own in any great abundance, ſhall yet if he liue vertuouſly, and walk in the feare of God, and in the obedience of his holy commandements, be more reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by many degrees, in the ſoules and conſciences of all that know (yea of thoſe alſo that doe ſlaunder and enuy, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne him) than the moſt wealthy man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen wanting theſe things. <hi>Iohn</hi> had more reuerence in <hi>Herods</hi> heart, then <hi>Herod</hi> amongſt all his courtiers and ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, though he wanted all that cap and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6017:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>knee wherewith <hi>Herod</hi> imagined himſelfe to be lifted vp to heauen in eſtimation. Yea, and if a rich man haue this credite (as <hi>Dauid, Iob, Abraham,</hi> and others had,) it is not his wealth but his goodneſſe (which doth nothing at all depende vppon his wealth) that brings the ſame vnto him: for a low eſtate giues occaſion to exerciſe as many vertues, and ſhew as much grace, (let <hi>Iob</hi> be witneſſe) which they that be wiſe (whoſe commendation alone is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable) will alſo ſee and obſerue, as the moſt high and exalted. And wherin then is wealth to be regarded for credite ſake? but that wee are fooliſh, and miſcall that credit which is but flattery; or at the leaſt but complementall trouble and vexation? But if it can doe no great good,<note place="margin">2. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing euill from thee.</note> yet I hope it can keepe away much euill from mee (will ſome man thinke) and make me ſafe in the day of danger. Let vs a litle conſider ſeriouſly of that point too; and if you find that it be as little able to defend againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harmful thing, as to procure any good, you will not then ſurely deny, but that it may well be called a lie, as the holy Ghoſt in this reſpect doth terme it; becauſe he
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6017:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>is neuer a whit the ſafer that hath it. Now then all euils are either ſpirituall or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, ghoſtly or bodily. The ghoſtly, are firſt,<note place="margin">Sonle.</note> ſinnes and luſts of our ſoule, as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God and his will, pride, vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, enuie, malice, filthy deſires, froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vniuſtice, a lying, a blaſphemous tongue, and the like. And will a golden plaiſter heale theſe diſeaſes? Let experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſpeake, and let the heart of euery one of you giue anſwere to this queſtion. Will a plaiſter made of golde and ſiluer heale theſe diſeaſes? Ah no, no: the whole world can tell it doth the contrary: rather cauſing them to feſter and ranckle; yea, and building a ſtrong caſtle for euery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affection, to poſſeſſe the heart of them that haue it, with ſo much more might and tyrannie: wealth makes a warm neaſt for ſin to ſit and hatch in, as we ſhal ſhew anon. A man ſhall not ouercome his luſts a whit the ſooner, or the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, when his purſe is full, his houſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, his grounds ſtored, his reuenues doubled, not theſe temporall, but ſpirituall weapons, the edge whereof is rather dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by wealth, doth ouercome ſuch ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6017:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>It is weeping, mourning, praying, and crying to God, it is euen godly ſorrow, that as a good plaiſter heales the ſoule, and wealth doth rather fill men full of laughter and Iollity, &amp; earthly delights, in which hee that liues is dead whileſt hee liues: that Chriſt might well ſay; <hi>Woe be to you that are rich, woe be to you that laugh.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iames, Howle yee rich men, for ye haue liued in pleaſure:</hi> and by conſequent in ſinne vp to the eares, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian mourning, onely keepes a Chriſtian ſoule in good temper. Yea, that one luſt of couetouſneſſe which wealth ſeemes moſt of all able to vanquiſh, yet it cannot. Money will not cure couetouſnes, more than wood &amp; oyle can quench fire. Wee ſee it and wonder, that euen this luſt is not leſſened, but encreaſed rather with it, as thirſt with ſome hariſh and ill-brued drinke, or wine which the Vintner hath adulterated with brimſtone, or ſome ſuch like geere. The more a man drinks of this, the more drought. The more a man hath, commonly the more worldly. And for the diuell and an ill conſcience with the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of it, we know that Sathan can ſhake,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:6017:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>affright, and terrifie a rich man as ſoone, and as much, as a poore. When God ſets the diuell and an ill conſcience looſe, they feare not an heape of golde, a faire houſe, a ſilken coate, a great liuing, nay not a throne and Scepter, but will as tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly, gnaw the ſoule of him that hath all theſe things, as if hee wanted all. A gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tiſſue can no more keepe a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken bone from aking, than a rich eſtate an ill conſcience from vexing. Yea, and the ſcorching flames of hell will burne, frie, and conſume the ſoule of ſuch, with as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious torture as the pooreſt varlets. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the rich glutton <hi>Diues</hi> in the Goſpel. So that the ſoule is no whit the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from ſin, from temptation, from horror, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> damnation, becauſe of wealth, &amp; is it not ſufficiently proued, that wealth is worth nothing? But what ſay you to temporall euils, will not money preſerue a man from their danger neither? Not at all, common ſence can tell vs.</p>
            <p>For it cannot driue away the gout, the ſtone, the ſtrangury, the collick, the feauer, the plague, the headache, the toothach; Yea, a fellon, or a whitloe, or the ache of a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6017:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>finger, nor the greateſt, nor the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of bodie, will be afraide of riches, his foot will ſtumble at a ſtone, his ſkinne, his bones, breake as ſtone, that hath them, as that wants them. Theſe griefes, as the frogs of <hi>Egipt,</hi> enter into rich-mens hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, creep vpon rich-mens bodies, yea they are rather more ſubiect to diuers euils, becauſe of their ouer-abundant fare and daintineſſe, and yet doe not enioy their plenty, becauſe they are commonly cloyd with too much, and to him that is full, an hony combe is bitter. So that theſe mens houſes are as much troubled with badde ſtomacks, with conſumptions, with Ohs, cryings, &amp; complaints, as the meaner ſort. If you ſay but they can hire phiſitions, I anſwere, it is true, but the phiſition cannot heale the diſeaſe: yea, ſometimes hee kils them with too many drugs, and the poore man hath better phiſicke, better cheape. His painful labor, and his moderate fare, is better to him, than a colledge of phiſitions.</p>
            <p>Alſo impriſonment, reſtraint,<note place="margin">3. Eſtate.</note> confining and baniſhment, doth as ſoone befall to them, as to their leſſe wealthy neighbors, as all ages witneſſe, and all ſtories. Nay,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6017:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>I will yet adde one thing more, that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more ſtrange than all this; wealth cannot keepe a man from pouerty, from beggery. And becauſe I know you wil all deny this, I will bring in 70. Kings at a time, to take their oaths vpon it. Looke in in the firſt of <hi>Iudges,</hi> and there you ſhall ſee 70.<note place="margin">Iudges 1.6.7.</note> Kings with their fingers, and toes cut off glad like whelps to licke vp crums at another Kings table. And then a little while after, you ſhall ſee that the ſame King which made all them ſo poore is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſame maner himſelf. What beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars-brat, could haue come to more need?</p>
            <p>Now deny if you can, that a rich man may die a beggar, as well as hee that is ſo borne. And I pray you doe but aske your owne memories, if they cannot tell of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in their owne knowledge, that from great wealth came to a morſell of bread, whoſe youth ſwimming in dainties, their elder yeeres would haue ſnapt at a cruſt, as we ſay, and beene glad of any releefe, and that alſo in many, not through their owne default. And yet is not wealth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable? Againe, for inward troubles that be naturall, as griefes, cares, iealouſies
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6017:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>and feares,<note place="margin">4. Minde for natural reſpects.</note> wee know that as cobwebs breed ſooner vnder wainſcote and faire hangings, than vpon a plain wall: ſo theſe ariſe in greater meaſure to them that are moſt clogd with plenty, as whoſe liues in all mens ſight doe moſt ſhew it, and if they doe at any time want them, not their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney but ſome other thing doth free them from the ſame. But yet perhaps wealth may mittigate the paine of a croſſe, though it cannot keepe it off? Indeed of all the profitable effects,<note place="margin">3. For mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euill.</note> this is the leaſt &amp; low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; but wealth is too baſe and weake to effect any ſuch mittigation. When a rich man lies ſicke of any diſeaſe, hath hee one pang leſſe? or is he able to beare one pang more patiently, becauſe hee can make a greater Inuentory than his neighbours? or when hee is falne into pouerty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, doth it aſſwage? (nay doth it not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther augment) the ſorrow that once he was in this and this place &amp; abundance? If a libell or a falſe report be caſt out againſt him, doeth it ſting or nettle him, leſſe, or not rather more than another? Nay doe wee not ſee, that becauſe it makes the hart bigger, it makes alſo the croſſe heauier
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:6017:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>commonly? ſo that a meaner man could with fewer cryes and lamentations lay fiue Children in the graue, than he can carry out one. A poore man could with leſſe vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, beare an hundred ill words and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings than he the leaſt croſſe-word. Of all men ordinarily none vexe themſelues more vnder a croſſe than the wealthy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they leaſt looke for it: and wealth we know cannot buy patience, becauſe not wiſedome and godlineſſe that are the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and nurſes of patience. But yet will ſome man ſay, the rich man hath a fire when another man ſits cold; the rich man is warme clad, when another is ſubiect to winde and weather; he fares well, when an other is hungry. I anſwere, hee is as free from colde that goes in frize or carſey, as he that is in ſattin and veluet: and it hath not yet beene brought to light, that the warmth of veluet is more wholeſome, or more comfortable, than that of frize. Alſo hee ſleepes as well that lyes vpon a flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or a pad of ſtraw, as hee that hath his down-bed and pillowes, and his Arras co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, and the ſofteſt ſheetes. Yea, and he that hath but one diſh, or perhaps onely
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6017:63"/>bread and cheeſe, and now and then ſome warme meate, feeds as ſweetly, and with as good an appetite, digeſts as wholeſomely, and with as ſound a ſtomacke, as hee that hath dainties brought to his table from the furtheſt quarters of the world: ſo that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the man that hath but enough for food &amp; raiment, is at leaſt his equal, that hath an ouerplus; and not the rich mans ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but his competency doth afford him theſe benefits, which diuers times are made more vnſauory, neuer more able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and content by their ouer-plentious ſtore: and wee tooke in hand to ſhew, not that ſufficient for meate, drink, and cloath, to content nature (which is the meaſure wherewith God limits our deſires) but a ſuperfluitie of things (which couetouſnes aimes at) is vnprofitable, &amp; worth nothing. Which ſeeing it can bring neither health, contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor good name, neither grace, vertue, nor forgiuenes of ſins, ſeeing it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not driue away ſin, Sathan, hell, death, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pain, ſorrow, yea, or pouertie, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the torment of any of theſe, as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans heart will tell him that it cannot: In a word, ſeeing it wil not make a man liue
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:6017:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>one whit the longer, or with more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, nor die one whit free for pangs and griefe, nor gaine heauen, nor eſcape hell the ſooner when hee is dead? will you not ſee and confeſſe it to be a thing of naught? And may I not ſay, ceaſe from wealth, which hath no breath or ſtrength at all, for wherein is it to be eſteemed?</p>
            <p>And therefore though thy crooked heart is not willing to yeeld, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <note place="margin">How fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine it is.</note> yet thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot chooſe but be conuinced of this, that great riches are vnprofitable, and not worth a ruſh. But ſay it were not ſo little commodious, yea ſay that it could doe any of the fore. named things, yet I wil prooue to your conſciences, that it is not worthy your deſires, becauſe of the next property thereof, which is vncertaintie. It is like a runnagate ſeruant, a fugitiue, a plaine vagrant, which though he be big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boned and ſtrong and skilfull, and able to worke, yet no man greatly cares for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee will be gone when a man hath moſt neede of him, and perhaps alſo take ſomething away with him that was more worth than all his ſeruice. So wealth will take its heeles when a man hath moſt vſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:6017:64"/>for it, and carry contentment away too, which is more precious than all the falſe happineſſe that it could procure whileſt it remayned with vs. This wealth hops from man to man, and place to place, as a light winged bird, from tree to tree. And no man can ſay where it wil rouſt at night. The holy Ghoſt hath compared it to a wilde foule, moſt ſwift of wing, and ſtrong in flight, ſaying;<note place="margin">Prou. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>Riches takes it ſelfe to it wings, and flyes away.</hi> Not like a cocke or hen, or ſome tame houſe-bird, that a man may follow and cath againe, no nor like an hawke that will ſhew where ſhe is by her bels, and be called againe with a lure; but like an Eagle, that mounts aloft paſt ſight, and is caried away with ſo much haſt that nothing will recall her. And where is the man that can clippe the wings of this eagle, when it is in his owne cuſtodie, that it ſhall not be gone from him when hee thinkes leaſt of it? If it could procure any benefit to your liues, you ſee it were not yet worth your wiſhes, nor your toyle, for it departs when you ſhould vſe it; and that without taking leaue: and then as he that riſeth from a ſtoole, and thinketh to ſit
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6017:65"/>downe againe, the ſtoole being remooued, takes the more dangerous knocke; ſo the minde that relyed on wealth, when it miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, is more tormented with vexation by the vntruſtineſſe thereof. And ſurely who hath liued ſo litle a while, but he hath ſeene wealth run away from many a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and neuer came at him againe to his dying day? Yea, &amp; ofttimes alſo leaue him to hunger, thirſt, nakedneſſe, and all miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and reproch: yea, though here his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers haue been at great toyle, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps hazarded a ſoule or two to get it. Yea it hath ſerued many a Lord, Nobleman, and great Prince thus vntruſtily, and yet will we not take warning but truſt it, doate vpon it? The holy Ghoſt cals it a lie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will ſurely play him ſuch ſlippery prankes, that hath confidence in it (as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man hath in that meaſure he deſires it) and a ſhadow, becauſe euery cloud that flies ouer the Sunne may (and that which is not to a ſhadow) irrecouerably cut it off. No man can promiſe himſelf to be weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy till night, one coale of fire, one vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed word, two falſe oaths, of two falſe vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines, (and how many ſuch be there in the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6017:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>world) may make him a beggar and a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner both at once? or if not ſo, yet he may go from it in a moment, as the rich man of whom Chriſt ſpeakes immediatly after my text, whoſe ſoule was called for, that night that hee ſang downe ſecure to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and when a man hath gotten goods not by right, and dyes in the midſt of his dayes, and leaues his wealth to another perhaps he knowes not, whom doth hee not prooue (that of himſelfe the which was true before, but neither himſelfe nor others would ſee, namely) that hee was a ſtarke foole? But all this is a little in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that which I haue to ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. It is not alone vnprofitable,<note place="margin">4. Hovv hurtfull it is too.</note> but hurtfull alſo, and exceeding dangerous to him that poſſeſſeth it, creating much euill to his body &amp; his ſoule, which harmfulnes procedeth not from the nature of wealth, but from the corruption of men; as cold drinke in it ſelfe is good, but not to him which hath the fit of an ague, yea to him, it is almoſt as bad as poyſon; and ſo, ſome meates are naught for men of ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, which they loue, but loue not them, and of theſe men are accuſtomed
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:6017:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>to take heede. Neither is this danger a whit the leſſe, becauſe it comes from our ill nature, not from wealth it ſelfe, ſeeing this corruption of nature cleaues to our ſoule, as faſt as the skinne to the fleſh, and wee ſhall aſſoone ceaſe to be, as to bee ſo euill. Yea, moſt of all, is it harmefull to him that moſt deſires it; and howſoeuer others may eſcape the hurt of it, yet hee cannot eſcape, ſeeing the ouerprizing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of bringeth forth the deſire, and both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether cauſe the danger. It may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very wel be likened to an artichoake, a little picking meat there is, not ſo whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as delicious, and nothing to that it ſhewes for; more than the tenth part is vnprofitable leaues; and beſides there is a coare in the midſt of it, which wil choke, not feed, and ſtrangle, not nouriſh, if a man doe not picke warily what hee puts into his mouth, better it is that God giue vs our portion, than ſet the whole diſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs; wee ſhall well-neare choake our ſelues with it; and ſuch a thing is wealth: yea, it is like ſome kinde of fiſhes, ſo full of ſmall and vnſeene bones, that no man eates it without great heede, but with great
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6017:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>danger, but a childe cannot ſcape perill if hee venture to eate it: and where ſhall we finde a man not a child in vnderſtanding? if any other be paſt a childe, yet certainly the man that loues wealth is not, It is like an head-ſtrong and luſtie horſe, that caſts the weake and vnskilfull rider, to the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his bones, if not his necke: and though children deſires to be on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, yet the father had rather keep them a foot: and certainly few haue the ſtrength to bridle and the skill to ſit and manage this reſtie ſteede, it is ſure none that loues to be vpon the back of it, hath skill in this horſemanſhip.<note place="margin">Bodily eſtate.</note> But wherein is it ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous will ſome man ſay? I anſwer, it is very troubleſome to the outward man, and like a luggring carriage makes him ſweate and puffe that goes vnder it. The rich mans plenty will not let him ſleepe, his varietie of diſhes brings him to ſurfetting, and that to many noyſome diſeaſes, and vnquiet nights, and dayes; and beſides, his eyes, his eares, his hands, his heart is not his owne, hee cannot be where he would faineſt, nor ſpeake nor thinke of what he moſt deſires, being called away by multitude of affaires,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6017:67"/>too too many ſtreames of buſineſſe doe driue him by force euen from himſelfe, and hee may well be called any mans ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, rather than his owne; ſo that in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward regards, when wealth growes very large, it is like a long coate or a garment too ſide, that a man treades vpon often, and catcheth a fall, when another goes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, eyther hee muſt holde it vp (and were it not as good be cut ſhorter?) or elſe it will bring him downe; yea, it makes men obnoxious to enuy, and ſo ſubiect to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, that none are more. As a tree that hath thick and large boughes, euery man deſires to lop him; beſides that, the ſidenes of his garment makes his owne feet ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: others alſo can more eaſily tread vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and giue him a fall; But all this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, a man might well eyther beare or preuent ſuch troubles. There follows an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ranck of miſchiefes out of the rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of wealth, that are more pernitious to the ſoule and cannot ſo well be ſhunned.</p>
            <p>It breeds many noyſome diſeaſes to the ſoule.<note place="margin">1. Soule. 1. Beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euils, Falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</note> Firſt it makes the ſoule very vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and falſly confident. Men thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo much more ſafe, by how much
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6017:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>more rich, and cannot be content to haue wealth, vnleſſe they doe alſo truſt vpon it; as <hi>Dauid</hi> on his hill, which yet deceiued him. The rich mans riches is a ſtrong tower to his imagination, ſaith <hi>Salomon;</hi> he takes himſelfe as it were walled and moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about by them, though indeed he lie as open to danger as other men. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it ſwels the hart with loathſome pride,<note place="margin">2. Pride.</note> making a man think himſelfe alſo ſo much the better, by how much, hee poſſeſſeth more. This diſeaſe as well as the former, the Apoſtle notes, ſaying to <hi>Timothy, Charge them that be rich in this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> 
               <hi>that they be not high minded, nor truſt in vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine riches:</hi> As if he had told vs that theſe two maladies, falſe confidence and an hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conceit of ones ſelfe, the purſineſſe of the minde, do ſo quickly enſue vpon great poſſeſsions, that few or none eſcape them. None can miſſe them without many war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, many earneſt exhortations, nay, nor ſcarce with them. This wealth is like ſtrong drinke to a weake braine, which ſends ſuch hote and fuming vapours vp into the ſame, that a man imagines he can hit the skie with his head, when he cannot
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6017:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtand vpright vpon his feete, yea, ſcarce keep himſelfe from tumbling in the mire. The monſtrous violence of fiery paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions into which, (as into fits of a burning ague) euery ſmall croſsing by an inferiour or equall, driues men of wealth, ſhewes what big conceits they haue of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. In a word, let examples here make the caſe plaine. Name a man almoſt that did not waxe proud by wealth, vnles God ſo ſauced his ſweet meate with the ſowre ſauce of affliction, that it was euen made vnſauory to him. It bred this frenzy in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzia, Aſa, Hezekiah,</hi> the beſt kings that the Scripture ſpeakes of; and if ſuch men could not beare it, what are wee? If any thinke though it made others worſe, it ſhall not make him ſo, let him know that this very conceit ſhewes him to be proud when he hath it not, and how would he be then if it were in his hands? thou art now conceited when thou art in a lower eſtate, will thy conceit of thy ſelfe diminiſh with the encreaſe of thy ſubſtance? Doeſt thou thinke God is ſo ill a diſpoſer of things that hee would not giue it thee, if he knew thou couldeſt vſe it moſt to his glory?
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6017:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>Giue God leaue to know what is in thee better than thy ſelfe, as the Phyſition knoweth the ſtate of the patients body when hee knowes it not. What child doth not thinke hee could vſe a knife well? but the wiſe father knowes his conceit ariſeth from ignorance: ſo I ſay to thee, that drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt wealth ſhould not make thee worſe. Art thou better than <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne? To ſay as the thing is, therefore God doth not giue ſo much of this wealth to his children, becauſe he knowes they would hurt themſelues with it, but giues a low eſtate to moſt of his ſeruants: for if they had more wealth, they would be ſo drunk with conceit, that they would think themſelues too good to ſerue him, as many men doe that haue it. And no wonder that riches bring a man to great pride: for they make him vtterly diſtaſte religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, which ſhould weane the heart from conceit of it ſelfe. Hee cannot haue while to pray, reade, meditate, for following his pleaſures, or ſeeking to adde more to that he hath, ſo that none doe ſeldomer viſite God in their cloſet, with true deuotion and feruent cryes than theſe, vnleſſe the Lord
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6017:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>fetch them in by a ſore croſſe, and then themſelues can ſee what harme their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie did vnto them.</p>
            <p>Then from pride growes ſecuritie;<note place="margin">3. Security</note> as a dead ſleepe from drunkenneſſe. Thoſe that haue their barnes and houſes full, as the rich man after my text, if they be not ſo wholy paſt ſence as in words to take vp his note, and ſay; Soule, ſoule, eate and drinke, and take thine eaſe: yet indeede fall iuſt to this practiſe, nuzling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this world, as an hogge in ſtraw, and giuing themſelues to ſeeke their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, profits, and promotions, and are ſo poſſeſſed with their owne thoughts, <hi>viz.</hi> how to get ſuch a liuing, ſuch a faire houſe, ſuch a match for this daughter, ſuch a thing for this ſonne, that ſcarce once in a moneth or an yeare, they can haue time ſeriouſly to thinke of getting heauen for themſelues, or for their children; yea, and though they haue ſome good thoughts put into their hearts by a good ſermon, or good exhortation, they die all, like a ſparke of fire for want of blowing; and adding too more fewell; I would theſe things did neede any proofe, and it were
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6017:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>not ſo plaine, that all can ſee it, but thoſe that feele it.</p>
            <p>Yea ſometimes wealth breeds that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table licentiouſneſſe (where it is growne to a great floud) that it makes men not to care what they do,<note place="margin">4. Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> but commit whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and other as foule ſinnes, euen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, becauſe no man, ſcarce their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whom they wil likely chooſe for their owne turne, ſcorning to ſuffer the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome plainneſſe of him that ſcornes to flatter; ſcarce I ſay, their miniſters dare tell them they offend. Yea, they promiſe to themſelues, by money and friends, to out-face Iuſtice it ſelfe, and peruert righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgment; ſo that when none keeps them from ſinne by reproofe, nor drawes them to repentance by iuſt puniſhment, they may goe to hell without rub, as a bowle downe an hill in a ſmooth place, the matter being referred to the laſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the iudge of all fleſh, who will iudge them ſo much more ſeuerely, by how much they boare out ſinnes on earth with more quietneſſe and ſafety.</p>
            <p>And leaſt men ſhould thinke only the worſt men fell to theſe ſickneſſes, by fat
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:6017:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>paſtures, behold <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man after Gods owne heart, who in his abundance ſtood vpon his hill vaunting himſelfe, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>He ſhould neuer be mooued;</hi> and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly fell to adultery, to murther, to ſuch hardneſſe in both, as not to confeſſe them of a long time; and had not God ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turned him, wealth would haue brought him to the diuell; and this is the good it doth euen to good men, except God doe chaſtiſe them euery morning and euery night, and make them ſober by many tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, that a poorer man ſhall ſcape. In one word therfore, the richer any man is, vnleſſe he pray more, and bewaile his ſinnes more, and think more of his latter end, the worſe he is, and if God doe not croſſe him more than others; he will pray leſſe than others.</p>
            <p>Wherefore vnleſſe his wealth be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed by more pinching afflictions, and then who would wiſh it?<note place="margin">1 Hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> he cannot but be a greater ſinner than other men. And ſay hee be Gods childe, yet hee growes farre ſlower in grace: others profite more at one ſermon than he at ten; others make more feruent prayers, and haue more holy
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6017:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>meditations in a moneth, than he in a year; and thinke more of heauen in a day, than hee in a moneth; ſo that Chriſt may well call riches the thornes that do euen choke the word, and therefore they doe alſo make the way to Heauen harder.<note place="margin">1. Grace</note> The ſame meanes that drawes poorer men to ſaluation, will not doe him: hardly can a rich man goe to heauen, it is as thicke clay in his iourney, that makes a man goe ſoftly. Not many rich men are ſaued, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> And how hard it is for him that hath riches to enter into heauen? ſaith he that cannot lye or be deceiued. Now let them goe and boaſt of their happineſſe, that makes them more proud, ſecure, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious than other men, and makes the way of grace, and the way of life to bee much more difficult and tedious to them than other men; and who would bee ſo greedy of that which the more hee hath, the leſſe vertuous hee ſhall be, if hee bee not more afflicted, and ſhall finde it more difficult to be ſaued: wherefore if any of you haue doated on wealth heretofore, let him ſeriouſly conſider and ponder vpon this, how fickle it is, how little good
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:6017:71"/>it can doe, how much hurt it will doe; and I aſſure my ſelfe and him too, hee ſhall ſoone grow leſſe in loue with it, if hee will be led by reaſon and truth, not by faſhion and opinion.<note place="margin">Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all.</note> And thus Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren I haue according as I was able, ſhewed you what couetouſneſſe is, the cauſes, effects, ſignes, and remedies. Try your ſelues by this deſcription and theſe ſignes, fright your ſelues from it by theſe cauſes and effects, and heale your ſelues of it by theſe remedyes. Suffer your ſoules to be wrought vpon, and let the ſucceſſe of your hearing be good, you are neerer damnation by this Sermon, if you mend not the fault reproued, neerer ſaluation, if you will take warning: let not the word be a ſauour of death to any of you. It comes to my minde, what is ſaide in the Goſpell, when Chriſt had ſpoken againſt couetouſneſſe, the Phariſes that were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous heard theſe things and they laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to ſcorne, as if hee had diſgraced couetouſneſſe onely becauſe hee wanted wealth. If theſe ſpeeches finde no better effects, how ill haue wee beſtowed our time? Be not as bad as Phariſes, I beſeech
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:6017:71"/>you, contemne not the ſpeaker, deride not the word of God, but heare it, beleeue it, practiſe it, condemne the ſinne, leaue the fault, beware of couetouſneſſe, and be that which no couetous man can be, true Chriſtians, and true bleſſed men: which God graunt for his Sonnes ſake Chriſt Ieſus, to whom with the Father &amp; the holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
